<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glasse of mans folly and meanes to amendment, for the health and wealth of soule and body. This glasse of mans folly, is that we may know, the cause of the cruelty, which dayly doth flow. ...</title>
            <author>B. H., fl. 1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12562A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853625</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1175:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glasse of mans folly and meanes to amendment, for the health and wealth of soule and body. This glasse of mans folly, is that we may know, the cause of the cruelty, which dayly doth flow. ...</title>
                  <author>B. H., fl. 1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], [70] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. C[reede] for I. H[arrison],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author's dedication to 1595 edition signed: B.H.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The edition statement is printed after "body" on title page.</note>
                  <note>This edition omits the dedication.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alcoholism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19017:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19017:1"/>
            <p>THE GLASSE OF MANS FOLLY, <hi>AND</hi> MEANES TO AMENDMENT, <hi>for the health and wealth of ſoule</hi> and body.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <q>
               <l>This Glaſſe of Mans folly, is that we may know,</l>
               <l>The cauſe of the cruelty, which dayly doth flow.</l>
               <l>Such powling, ſuch pilfring, ſuch gryping for gaine,</l>
               <l>And great greedy gathering, as purchaſe our paine.</l>
               <l>Such Whores and ſuch Theeues, Bankrouts, and Beggers,</l>
               <l>Quarrellers, Fighters, and mercileſſe Murtherers.</l>
               <l>Such wrangling for wealth, and care for to get,</l>
               <l>Such loſſe of ſoule health, as canker ſhall fret.</l>
               <l>Such euill, and ſuch enuy, heart-hatred, and ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Such ſeruing of Sathan betweene Man and Wife.</l>
               <l>In this Booke is ſhewed, <hi>diabolus</hi> deuiſes,</l>
               <l>And alſo reproued, his ſubtill enterpriſes.</l>
               <l>Therefore (gentle Reader) deale thou not ſo raſhly,</l>
               <l>To reproue with reproching the thing that miſlikes thee.</l>
               <l>The Learned allowes this, which vertue imbrace,</l>
               <l>For none but ill actions, it ſeekes to deface.</l>
               <l>And if it doe touch thee, turne prating to praying,</l>
               <l>Least <hi>Zelotipus Deus,</hi> correct thy gaine-ſaying.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>T. C.</hi> for <hi>I. H.</hi> 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19017:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19017:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO LOVERS OF</hi> VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and Haters of vice, bee Grace and Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed &amp; deerely bought by <hi>Ieſus,</hi> this <hi>booke</hi> doth diſprooue, that moſt doe loue, and is liable to the leaude.</p>
            <p>It is like that ſuch as loue theyr ſinnes heerein reprooued, will miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like it, &amp; mee, for reproouing: for ſtrikers at vices, are ſtrooke with calumnies. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to Gods children is my dedication, to patronize it when the impious deſpiſe it. I made it that God may be <hi>glorified,</hi> you comforted, the wicked rebuked. I beſeech you accept it, as a Mite caſt among greater Teaſures, for Gods word is the warrant. If any obiect there be many good books extant, It is requiſite: for people be many, &amp; ſinnes do multiplie: Grudge at no good bookes, grieue for ſinne. Wee may admire and lament for thoſe of ridiculous Ribauldrie, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogates Gods glorie. The Inuenter, Printer, Seller, and Buyer, muſt remember they are meanes to winne the diuell darlings. It is odious how by many they are peruſed and iterated, but the good refuſed. It doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgate that ſathan win and winew vs, &amp; that the tares his Adherents, ſpring thicker then the good Corne.</p>
            <p>It is grieuous to thinke how wee grieue our good God. Impietie is ſo ſpred that there was neuer more neede of reproofe. The beſt Bookes pleaſe not the proude, <hi>Momus</hi> maligneth. Herein is expreſſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for the contrite, ſeuerity for the obſtinate, whoſe ſtonie hearts deſerues hammers, for them ſharpe ſpeech is requiſite. <hi>Valete.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19017:3"/>
            <head>Combibo counſelleth not to be counſelled, and would the Author alter.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHy trouble you my merry minde?</l>
               <l>I cannot loue nor like yee:</l>
               <l>Vnto my corps you are vnkinde,</l>
               <l>So much to moue and minde mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is your loſſe it gets no gaine,</l>
               <l>Your Pen your profite hinder:</l>
               <l>For to refraine from pot is paine,</l>
               <l>My ioy is carnall pleaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Mates and I will looke awry,</l>
               <l>With frowning face wee view yee:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Boore Bibax</hi> back-bites bitterly,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Superbia</hi> doe iniure thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Capillatus</hi> hee will worke thee hate,</l>
               <l>If you make bookes to braide vs:</l>
               <l>Wee are at eaſe, com, be our mate,</l>
               <l>In pleaſures great not grieuous.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Astutia</hi> will thee deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aleator</hi> caſteth in his lot:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salax</hi> againſt thee doth deuiſe;</l>
               <l>Refuſe thy Pen, let's fill the pot.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Constancie conſented to.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Feare not the face of <hi>Fancie</hi> fine,</l>
               <l>No leaud life, nor loue luſt?</l>
               <l>Seeke thou the ſafetie of their ſoules,</l>
               <l>In God put thou thy truſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy Booke good people well doth like,</l>
               <l>Send forth therefore this <hi>Doue;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To bring with ioy in <hi>Arke</hi> aright,</l>
               <l>By meanes of <hi>God</hi> his loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pray thou to <hi>God</hi> this worke to bleſſe,</l>
               <l>That it may hale to Heauen:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> glorious is, all praiſe to him,</l>
               <l>Good people ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Optime Deus esto nobiſcum, nunc &amp; in auum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19017:3"/>
            <head>THE GLASSE OF MANS FOLLIE.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough little conſidered of ſome, (yet are they not ignorant of this) that we ſhuld liue according to Gods will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in his word, &amp; be carefull to win each other; dooing our induſtry to ſhew the things he hath commaunded, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and reproouing that hee hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. And amitie doth animate vs to illuſtrate Gods glorie in all our actions, (which is the finall cauſe of mans Creation) therefore mentioned in this <hi>praeludium.</hi> Such follow not their pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſies, as our aduerſaries of the truth doe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 97.7.</note> for ietting Ieſuits and bloody Papiſts call ſtocks and ſtones Laye-mens bookes, yet God <hi>Omniſcient</hi> doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince it. <hi>Confounded be all they that ſerue grauen Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that boaſt themſelues of Idolles. <hi>Eſay,</hi> 42.8. I am the Lord, that is my Name, and my glorie will I not giue to any other, neither my praiſe to grauen Images.</hi> Saint <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth vs the true way that directed him right,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.105</note> 
                  <hi>Thy Word is a lampe vnto my feete, and a light vnto my path.</hi> In which as in a myrrour if wée ſearch with true prayer, we ſhall ſée light more fulgent then the bright Sun beames, to ſhewe vs the way to walke to Gods glorie. From which Canonicall rule Sathan makes an aberaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Therefore in hate to him, and loue to man, here is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued, Not vſing the Victuling-houſe for neceſſitie, but the common and accuſtomed ſinne of Drunkenneſſe, that daily increaſeth: From which except with ſpéede wée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine, wée procure Gods high diſpleaſure to be powred euer vpon vs.</p>
               <p>The Apoſt. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> indued with a heauenly ſpirit, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing <hi>future</hi> things, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>praemunition,</hi> giueth a <hi>caueat; <hi>2.</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19017:4"/> Timoth: <hi>3. This know alſo that in the laſt dayes, perillous times will come; for men ſhall be louers of theyr owne ſelues,</hi>
                  </hi> which is to be vnderſtood of the inordinate loue of theyr bodies, for while we liue ſo, wée are enemyes to our ſoules, which are our ſelues. <hi>Corpora noſtra non ſunt nos.</hi> Our bodyes are not vs, <hi>Rom: <hi>8.12.</hi>
                  </hi> To the which wée are debters, but not to liue after the fleſh. Yet till wée the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and fainte the ſoule: delighting ſo in liquor that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to we luſt. Belly-gods abuſe theyr bellyes, they can ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe at all times, thyrſtie or not, aſmuch in one day as might ſerue ſome men ten: So impudent and ſhameleſſe, that they rather boaſt thereof then bée aſhamed. <hi>Bibax</hi> addicted to <hi>Bibaculus,</hi> in Cliant to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> frequenting <hi>Bachanal</hi> till he be <hi>Bacchatus.</hi> The deceyuer inticeth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to torment vs. Some ſeldome ceaſe, but are exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goodnes, flexible to follie, pliant to impietie, with delectation in ſuch dooings. Theyr odious actions ſhewes affections are not fixed on God to loue him, and with feare to offend him, except a ſeruile feare, as Sathan hath, it is to be feared, ſome want it. For though ſome doo boaſt they are ſaued by Chriſt, they denie him in theyr déedes. The fruits bewrayes the heart to be falſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God:</hi> their déedes ſay, ſo doo they. The ſucking ſinne is as common as the Cartway, which is to be deplored, and daylie reprooued. Much <hi>feſtinacion</hi> not to be faſting, to fatting, turning pot after potfull into wide weaſands, and bias bellies making them gutters of gulpers, and ſwiltubs for ſwyne. Vnſatiable in receiuing, and ready in expelling, néere the Dore ſo perſpicuous, as theyr priuities may be perceiued. Then againe, into the Den with an <hi>Anthem,</hi> fill &amp; fetch, haue for halfe, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>ariditie,</hi> yet a pint at a draught drawing deſtruction. <hi>Cauponula</hi> catcheth them, the Tap-tarrier inticeth them, to powre in pots plentifully, trip and turne a Dye dainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſweare and ſtare, iet and ieſt, cogge and lye leaudly, in the blind Ale-houſe not licenced, where the Hoſt ſits halfe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19017:4"/> rotten, voyd of fealtie, full of fallacie, like the Image in time of blindneſſe, which ſhaked the head merilieſt to them that gaue moſt: So exceſſe makes men beaſts and worſe; <hi>Modum adhibent apperitui,</hi> They meaſure their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites by the rule of neceſſitie: but men with reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnreaſonable, of whom it is written, <hi>Eſay 22.23. Let vs eate and drinke, for to morrow we ſhall dye. <hi>Ede, bibe, lude,</hi>
                  </hi> is the Epicures felicitie. Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be loſt;</hi> but they ſpill and ſpoyle. <hi>Combibo</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous till <hi>Colon</hi> cracke,<note place="margin">Bibbers are bountifull to abuſes, not to good vſes.</note> hee blowes and boaſts he muſt not be miſerable, not remembring the miſery of thouſands ready to miſcary for want of that hee waſtes. <hi>Math. 5. Bleſſed are the mercifull;</hi> but exceſſiue Suckpots ſhew themſelues miſcreants without comiſeration, <hi>ſympathy,</hi> or fellow-feeling of famiſhed folks and children. They pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie not their owne ſpirituall miſery how Satan deludes them of the <hi>Beniſſon;</hi> but are foggie, full of faſtiuitie, loth to linquiſh, like to languiſh, and illiterated, not knowing a letter, he fils the Chimney end with <hi>Praebibo tibi;</hi> and Lice often fitter for that place then Latine. Lazie Lads likes it, and calles for liquor liuely. <hi>Meretrix</hi> is an inticer to the ſlaughter. The lewde are delighted; for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue not impietie, but get impiouſly, and ſpend prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, till that got with a reach, is loſt by a ſtretch. True dealers are ſpighted, which miſlikes their miſdoings, and ſpends as riches extends. There be Victualers farre off and neere me, that honour God by their victualing: they reprooue their gueſts for great drinking, rude talke, and ſwearing, not hauing their houſes dennes for Diuels. Some others, like <hi>Proteus</hi> (which would change him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to al likenes) frame themſelues as euery man is affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioned, flattering thoſe that plye the pot faſteſt; no aſſidui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie delayed. So youth prooue poore, and without a penny, departs in anxietie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 15.13.</note> The prodigall ſonne waſted his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with riotous liuing, ſo long as laſted his portion he was in eſtimation; but when all was gone hee would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19017:5"/> haue filled his belly with the huſks that the Swine did eate, and no man gaue vnto him. Euen ſo, when men are poore and purſe empty, their abſence is liked more then their company. Yet people, whoſe delight is to péepe into a pot, will not be warned; but may be compared to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt. Eth.</hi> 3.10.</note> which wiſhed his necke longer then a Cranes, to féele the more pleaſure in the long running downe: which minde is farre from the faithfull, whoſe affection is in heauen. Therefore, yée Corpulents, all for the corps, that frequent quaffing and ryot, like vntamed Tigers, and bruites vnbridled, if you would vſe militarie reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt <hi>Mille-artifex,</hi> which conquers you like Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, yée would tame your bodies, and nouriſh your ſoules: but not féeling his circumuents, yée liue to your luſts, yée drinke and eate at eaſe, not hauing the combat Gods children haue. O, let vs repent, leſt wee haue our portion in this life.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 17.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Lament. 3. It is of the Lords mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that we are not conſumed.</hi> To him be all honour for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sit laus Sanctae Trinitati.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Effects of drowſie Drunkenneſſe.</head>
               <p>THe receipt of mens money ſuperfluouſly ſpent is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to a good conſcience. Their wiues and children want ſuſtenance, ſhee knowes not at what Alehouſe to finde him: and ſéeing her goods conſuming, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren crying, ſhe tels him his fault, and intreats him to be frugall. The Béere piercing his braine, hee counts her counſell hoſtilitie: he ſtamps &amp; ſtaggers, ſtares, ſweares, &amp; blaſphemes the Almightie, which hideous othes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods wrath is kindled. He giues her blowes, no béefe, whereby loue decreaſeth, hatred increaſeth. When they ſhould pray, they prate, and depart, or liue peruerſely. The patrimony might haue maintained family hoſpitalitie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19017:5"/> and béene left to the poſteritie: but two yeeres drinking cauſed the diſſipation. The ſequell is euill; great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance to good people, whome they couſen, théeue, and purloine from, procuring the Priſon: there they haue hunger, thirſt, cold, lameneſſe, lice, loathſome, noyſome: a Dogges death is procured, which was by meanes of waſting. At the Gallowes they cry out of Alehouſes, euill inticers, licentious liuing, drunkenneſſe, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, theft, and chambering, which earſt would not bee told of; neither will many that now are diſſolute: but powre into the paunch, till (alaſſe) had-land is lowſie.</p>
               <p>Good Hoaſts fore-ſée this, and giue good counſell: but an <hi>(Antitheſis)</hi> euill Hoaſt doeth not; they and their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league companions are flexible, but to vertue aduerſe. Hee that idely ſpends his patrimony, deſerues this <hi>Epithete; (Spend-thrift,)</hi> but ſuch as conſume it in Drunkenneſſe, are execrable creatures.</p>
               <p>O yee conſumers, yee are theeues to your families, enemies to God and to your owne ſoules and bodies, and robbers of all the needy. Woe bee to ſuch as cauſe the poore to cry, and procure GOD to withdrawe his bleſſing from Lande and Sea. Yet <hi>Colon</hi> increaſeth <hi>Cholera,</hi> procuring profuſion, the full gorge foames froth. Preſent pleaſure ſeemes ſweete, not regarding that bitter gnaſhing followes quaffing: for it doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminate the ſoule. Exceſſe of colde Frumenty fills men full of infirmitie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Lot</hi> thereby committed luſt and inceſt. It cauſeth <hi>Lethargie</hi> and ſleeping, and quailes good qualities. <hi>Ierom. <hi>Venter mero aeſtuans ſpumat in libidinem:</hi>
                  </hi> The belly inflamed with Wine, burſteth foorth to luſt. Beere-belly is inflamed, but not aſhamed; yet the woe of woes is pronounced. Oh,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.11.</note> yee that can drinke at all times, and thinke it mellifluous to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate, as inſtigators intice others, wound not your ſoules with woes.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19017:6"/>
               <p>Refraine from quaffing, it is a <hi>Hecticke,</hi> inflaming the ſoundeſt parts of the body. It makes a good ſanguine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection puft; if not pocky: but dead drunke, pale. Quaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing makes men vnquiet, vntemperate, incontinent, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious, fierce, wrathfull to fight, curſe and brawle. It hurts the braines, head, eyes, and hearing, it cauſeth pluriſie, dropſie, to ſcorne, ieſt, and talke of bauldry: as a quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian Feuer, it inféebleth the whole man, bréeding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. It infecteth ſoule and body, and procures plagues from the Almighty: it deſtroyeth his benefits, and brings plenty to ſcarcitie, and cauſeth the poore, the aged, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to cry for foode. It offendeth the Omnipotent God, and is an offence to all Gods children. All kinde of ſinnes waite on exceſſe. It makes men prompt to euill, peruerſe to pietie: it gaines the Gallowes, and hell without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Yet <hi>Milleartifex,</hi> with excuſe, ſaith it makes him acute: but how? to ſerue <hi>Aſmodeus</hi> and <hi>Aſotus:</hi> and therefore to be reiected as <hi>Aſpis,</hi> very venemous. It makes none ingenious to goodneſſe, the euill effects are monſtrous. It dulles and takes away the ſences, ſets the eyes in the head anſtere and ſtrange to behold. It makes a man a monſter, metamorphoſed from the Image of God, to the image of the Diuell: their actions are irkſome to good people, though the rude reioyce to ſee it. Quaffing is the occaſion, if not the cauſe of felonious theeues, and flattering theeues (<hi>alias</hi> couſeners:) the firſt are dangerous; the laſt liker hypocrites, to inſinuate and ſay they loue you, but it is the adiunct of your purſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, but neuer paying. I reſtraine to particularize any by-qualitie or name, yet many deteine that is not their owne, but proſper not. The effect of drunkenneſſe and gluttony is pouerty:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe, ſorrow, contentions, bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, woundes without cauſe: redneſſe of eyes,</hi> are adioynts to them that tarry long at the wine. <hi>At the laſt it byteth like a Serpent, and ſtingeth like an Adder. Thine eyes ſhall beholde ſtrange Women,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19017:6"/> and thine heart ſhall vtter peruerſe thinges.</hi> Wine and Women leade wiſe men out of the way. The beſt wine and worſt women are prouokers. Much eating and drinking makes Idiocie and dotage, whereby men are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured to the vndiſcreet, as <hi>Herode, <hi>to graunt the head of bleſſed</hi> Iohn Baptiſt, <hi>to a deceytfull Dauncer.</hi> Hoſea <hi>4. Whoredome, Wine, and new wine, infatuates the heart.</hi>
                  </hi> Exceſſe makes men eſtranged from themſelues, excluding all honeſty &amp; humanity. Some cannot liue on their lands, nor others by good Occupations,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 107.</note> and therefore ſpoyled in priſons. A fruitfull Land is turned into barrenneſſe, for wickednes. Drunkenneſſe deſtroieth Gods benefits and doth auert his bleſſings. Yee Common-wealth conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, deuote not your ſelues to the Diuell. Your ſurſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting exceſſe, ſo raiſeth the price, that the poore ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine theyr Families, but are diſtreſſed, ſome diſtracted. Yée are the death and vndooing of thouſands. How can you anſwere for thoſe yée cauſe to ſtarue; and for the death of your ſelues, by your exceſſe? All the world haue the leſſe and worſe ſucceſſe for you. Millions of men haue beene vndone, by haunting ſuch Houſes,<note place="margin">Be counſelled</note> where they loſt their liuing, and learned leaudneſſe. Young men thinke on this (for your ſakes I write this) before your Land be gone, before yée be in thraldome, and diſ-franchiſed of your liberties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>before thine eyes be dimme, and thou tremble.</hi> Doe not procraſtinate; It is apparent, that ſuperfluous powring in of drinke, hath prouoked God to powre downe extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Flouds: and for your foaming out, to make the Sea breake out, whereby People haue periſhed, Cattell drowned, Goods and Bridges borne into the Ocean. The Skye cries againſt vs, Thunders are fearfull, Diuels ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Trées rent, Houſes brent, People killed, many things deſtroyed, God is diſpleaſed, winde and weather auerre it; oft, Ships are ſunke: Oh we are obdurate, we pull downe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19017:7"/> greater vengeance, and amend not. Manie vſe <hi>Dolus,</hi> to pamper theyr paunches with <hi>Diues,</hi> till with that <hi>Epulo,</hi> they taſte <hi>dolorificus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh ſoule, thinke how the diuell doth pollute thée, make not ſo much of thy bodie. Exceſſe brings not ſalubritie, nor ſanctitie, wholſomneſſe nor holineſſe, but contrarie. <hi>Prouerb. <hi>20. Wine is a mocker, ſtrong drinke is raging, and whoſoeuer is deceiued thereby is not wiſe.</hi>
                  </hi> Such are deceyued and vnwiſe as quaffe Quartes in a day, but one were better, and hée fitter to any good action. Yet protract they the time at Ale-houſes, and make their bodies vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable receptacles. Prouokers fat themſelues &amp; others for the day of ſlaughter, hindring manie, but profite not any.</p>
               <p>Oh a dearth is to be dread. Bée not a ſucking <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite,</hi> the mouth ſhalbe full of earth. Quaffing leades to the lake of quaking. Pray and repent.</p>
               <p>Our proſperitie, tranquillitie, and truth many yeares taught, will be witnes to reprooue vs, for want of loue to God, and for our ſelfe-loue to impiety.</p>
               <p>Conſider this yée that forget GOD. Be not brutiſh; they are worſe then Brutes, that are bond-ſlaues to euill Affections. Therefore hate that which God abhorreth: to him be all honour for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>DEO omnis Poteſtas &amp; Gloria.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Drunkenneſſe, and Exceſſe of drinking reprooued.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COmbibo</hi> perſwades his complices that they committe no Drunkenneſſe ſo long as they can talke and walk, although theyr Bellyes be bladder-blowne. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member oh Swyne, and manners worſe, what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith; <hi>Woe be vnto them them that are mightie to drink wine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>and men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drinke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now knowe that God hateth the inordinate Drinker, although hée doe not ſtagger.</p>
               <p>Some are gyddie by Age, Sicknes, or Imbecillity, yet
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19017:7"/> little drinkers: the Drones are the Drunkards; Woe, and the woe of woes are denounced to them. <hi>Eſay. <hi>5.11. Woe vnto them that riſe vp early in the Morning, that they may follow ſtrong drinke.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They haue woe and ſorrowe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>that tarrie long at the Wine.</hi> Yet <hi>Bibulus</hi> whoſe beſt behauiour is barbarous, vſeth the Ale-houſe, and abuſes it as an euill-houſe; woes will not warne him, hée neglecteth his Vocation, to the detriment of his Wife and Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But if any prouide not for his owne, and eſpecially, for thoſe of his owne Houſe, hee hath denyed the Faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and is worſe then an Infidell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many prouide for the wormes, that ſhall wring their corpulent Carcaſes. Chriſt giueth a <hi>Caueat, <hi>Luke,</hi> 21.34. Take heed to your ſelues, leaſt at any time your harts be ouercharged with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe.</hi> Let menacing or Admonition amend vs. <hi>Epheſians, <hi>5.18. And be not drunke with wine, wherein is exceſſe, but be filled with the Spirit.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas, the Carcas is filled, and the ſpirite of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. <hi>Heluo</hi> haſteth to hell, and gormondiſe his guts, till hee euacuates as hée receyued.</p>
               <p>A Swyne is a ſwallower, immoderate to moyſture, <hi>Matth. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </hi> The <hi>Gergeſenes</hi> loſt many into whom the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels entred, droue them into the Sea, &amp; drowned them in that moyſture; and the Diuels driue Swiniſh mindes, to drowne them with drinke. <hi>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</hi> Our eating and drinking muſt be to Gods glorie, to eate and drink to liue, and not liue to eate and drink. <hi>Drunkennes &amp; reuellings are fruits of the fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>they which do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God.</hi> A fearfull <hi>Enthymeme,</hi> to them not mortified. Imbrace the ſaying of <hi>S. Paule,</hi> not the pot. <hi>Let vs walke honeſtly as in the day, not in ryot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, not in cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bering &amp; wantonneſſe, nor in ſtrife &amp; enuying, <hi>but put yee on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13</note> 
                  <hi>and make not prouiſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſts therof.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19017:8"/>
               <p>Except wée abandon the déedes of darknes, we put not on the Lord Ieſus, but the diuell. To ſée him makes ſuch to quake: but they entertain him, ſerue him, and feare not. The Lord ſaith by the prophet <hi>Ioel, <hi>1.5. Awake ye drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, weepe and howle ye drinkers of wine:</hi>
                  </hi> Hee mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth and admoniſheth them to preuent the Anger to come. <hi>Ierem: <hi>35.6.</hi>
                  </hi> The <hi>Rechabites</hi> abſtained from drinking of wine, at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of <hi>Ionadab;</hi> Much more ought we to refraine from drunkenneſſe at Gods commaund. The Lord reprooueth the Adultrers, that loueſt agons of wine. The prophet complaineth, <hi>Eſay. <hi>56.12. Come yee (ſay they) I will fetch wine,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Oſea.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and wee will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drinke.</hi> That <hi>Come,</hi> driues to detriment, and we goe willingly. <hi>Math: <hi>11.28.</hi> Christ</hi> ſaith <hi>Come, for our comfort,</hi> but we will not: It's the faſhion to call and prouoke each other to exceſſe of drinking. It was not ſo, at that royall Feaſt, <hi>Heſter <hi>1.8. And the drinking was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the lawes, none did compell.</hi>
                  </hi> The great God, little regarded, denounceth woe to inticers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Woe vnto him that giueth his neighbour drinke, that putteſt thy bottle to him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Abac.</hi> 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and makeſt him drunken alſo, that thou mayeſt looke on his nakednes. <hi>Solomon</hi>
                  </hi> would drawe vs from the meanes that moueth delight to drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, leaſt we be drunken. <hi>Prou: <hi>23. Looke not vpon the wine when it is red.</hi>
                  </hi> Oh that Parents would not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, but ſage as <hi>Salomon,</hi> to counſell. It is odious and abſurd for youth to drinke much. Except in labor, <hi>a modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> ſuffiſeth nature. To giue wine to a young man, is to adde oyle to fire: Wine and ſtrong drinke are fitte for the weake and ſicke. <hi>Prou: <hi>31. Giue ſtrong drinke to him that is ready to periſh, &amp; wine vnto thoſe that are of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie hearts.</hi>
                  </hi> Alas, ſuch lacks, when lazie liuers gulps gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons, and iudge that thoſe which ioyne not with them, doo thinke themſelues righteous; but they that féele theyr ſinnes moſt, vſe meanes to tame their fleſh: So did pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Paule, <hi>1.</hi> Cor: <hi>92.7. I keepe vnder my bodie, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19017:8"/> bring it into ſubiection.</hi>
                  </hi> It appeares that pamperers are Iuſtitiaries and féele not theyr ſinnes, which defileth their ſoules. Did they, they would ſtriue and reſiſt it, and not ſo nouriſh it. Immoderate nutriment procures im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Dauid</hi> being thirſtie, deſired water, and it was brought him. Neuertheleſſe hée would not drinke.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam:</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>verſe 17.</hi> And he ſaide, <hi>Be it farre from mee ô Lorde, that I ſhould doe this; Is not this the bloud of the Men that went in ieopardy of theyr liues? Therefore hee would not drinke it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A carnall minde would thinke wine had bene fitter to ſtrengthen him againſt his viſible enimies: but being then not fit, Exceſſe with vs is much more vnfit, and to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained, that wée may ouercome our inuiſible enimies the diuels. He refuſed that he had néede of: much more ought we to refuſe néedleſſe exceſſe: ſuch effuſion cauſeth confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the lake of lamentation.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Daniel:</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Balthazar</hi> being drinking of his cups, heard and had a cooling. God graunt vs grace to be prepared, and in well dooing at Chriſts comming. <hi>Lamentat: <hi>3. It is of the Lordes mercies, that we are not conſumed:</hi>
                  </hi> to him he all honour for euer. <hi>Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A perfect proofe that Gods children muſt not be aſſociated with Drunkardes, nor with other impious.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAlomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be not amongſt wine bibbers. <hi>Prou:</hi> 24. Be thou not enuious againſt euill men, neyther deſire to be with them. <hi>Prou:</hi> 28. He that is a companion of riotous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhameth his father.</hi> The Pſalmographe ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro:</hi> 23.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal. <hi>26. I haue not ſate with vaine perſons, neither will I goe in with diſſemblers.</hi>
                  </hi> But Drunkards count ſuch no companions. They loſe a lofty title that ſhake not hands with the diuell. The foremoſt in leaud life is the bad. But it's better to be hated and goe to Heauen, then of them to beloued and goe to Hell. Vertue ſhall aſcend, when Vice
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19017:9"/> ſhall deſcend,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 4.</note> their amitie is enmitie. <hi>Whoſoeuer therfore wilbe a frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the world, is the enemy of God.</hi> Therfore good men dare not flatter them in follie. <hi>Pſ. <hi>139.21.</hi> Dauid hated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hated God. He ſhewes where the true harted ſhall dwell. Pſ. <hi>15.4. He ſhal abide in</hi> Gods <hi>tabernacle, in whoſe eyes a vile perſon is contemned, but honoreth them that</hi> feare the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim:</hi> 3.</note> But this world will grow to an <hi>Antipathie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euill people ſhall be eſteemed, and good people contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Yet if thou haſt ignominie refraine theyr company: for though thou be expert with a good Booke in thy boſome they will frame thée to theyr faſhion, and ſo to confuſion. If they cannot winne thee, they will wrong thée. They that are diſſolute of theyr duties to God, are careleſſe of theyr ſoules, and of thy ſafetie. It is a probabilitie, that their euocation and prouoking, is manie mens vndooing.</p>
               <p>Say then with the princely Prophet, <hi>Pſal: <hi>119.115. Depart from mee yee euill doers, I will keepe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of my God.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er: <hi>63. I am a companion of all them that feare the Lorde.</hi>
                  </hi> Bée thou ſo, and not a <hi>Chamelion</hi> for all companies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cato</hi> counſells thée to walke with good men. Shall an <hi>Ethnick</hi> excell vs in good conuerſation, that neuer had our meanes of conuerſion? Hée doth admoniſh vs, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth menace vs, <hi>Math: <hi>24. Hee that eateth and drinketh with the drunken, ſhall be appointed his portion with Hypocrites: there ſhalbe weeping &amp; gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Paule</hi> reproouing the impietie of people, ſhewing the wrath of God for the ſame, ſaith: <hi>Be not therefore parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.7.</note> They that let Drunkardes haue drinke may proſper a time, but ſuch gaine is like to prooue paine. Hée or ſhee that giue weapons to thoſe that wound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,<note place="margin">A Caueat to fillers to Drunkards.</note> are culpable. Thou art forbidden their companie and ſocietie. It is odious to attend them.</p>
               <p>Conſider this, yée that haue houſes for ſuch. Reprooue and remooue ſuch ſlowbellies, you had better doe any ſlaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie then be acceſſary to theyr actions. <hi>Math: <hi>16.26. For what is a man profited if he ſhall gaine the whole world,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19017:9"/> and loſe his owne ſoule?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Abhorre their behauiour though they hate thée, <hi>Ephe: <hi>5.11. And haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull works of darknes, but rather reproue them.</hi>
                  </hi> If they will not heare they are barbarous. <hi>Prou: <hi>12. Hee that hateth reproofe is brutiſh.</hi>
                  </hi> Win them with lenitie, elſe refraine their ſociety, <hi>2. <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.14. What communion hath light with darknes? <hi>Gen:</hi> 25.22. <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi>
                  </hi> ſtrugled in the wombe: So doe Gods ſeruants and ſathans adherents; and ſo did Chriſt and his Apoſtles with the wicked world. Let vs not ſerue ſin, but our good God, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be all honor for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Laudate IAH.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Drunkards hatred to thoſe that abhorre their behauiour.</head>
               <p>THe primarie prophet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.139</note> a Paragon of ardent amitie to God, ſaith: <hi>My zeale hath conſumed mee, becauſe mine enemies haue forgotten thy worde.</hi> A man to mourne for his owne ſinnes in ſinceritie, is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon: to mourn for ſins of others is not much in cuſtome. He was a mourner for his owne ſins, &amp; for the ſins of his enemies, which thing ſo admirable, fewe doo imitate. Yet when hée wept, it was to his reproch. <hi>He was a Prouerb, &amp; ſong of the drunkards;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods ſpirite excited him to reprooue ſuch as impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Gods glory. But malefactors could not, neither ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they abide ſuch miſlikers. Pſ. <hi>35. The abiects did teare him, &amp; with hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall mockers in feaſts, they gnaſhed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him with their teeth.</hi>
                  </hi> He ſaith, <hi>Falſe witnes did riſe vp: they laid to my charge things I knew not, they rewarded me euil for good, to the ſpoyling of my ſoule.</hi> Yet in their ſicknes he mourned, in his aduerſity they reioyced. It was, and will be falſe filbellies, hate their vnlike with crueltie. <hi>The ſighi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſinger of Iſrael had many enemies:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Patheticall affections are with afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</note> 
                  <hi>vnmercifulnes are adioynts to miſcrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, like tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in time of blindnes againſt the modeſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs being patients, when fierce age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts threw fagots on their faces: Effecting their craft without mercy, that the martyrs might not profeſſe their maiſter. Yet did they, eleuati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g harts &amp; ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds in fire &amp; flames, ſing pſalmes to God, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be all honor for euer. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19017:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Whether Papiſts or Atheiſts, ſome Alemates obſerue this <hi>Adage, No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo te, nec poſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicere quare:</hi> I like thée not, nor can I tell thee why: theyr <hi>Eglogue</hi> comes of enuie. But ſance for the falſe tongue,<note place="margin">Byrche for black tongues</note> are <hi>Pſal: <hi>120. Sharpe arrowes of the mightie, with coles of Iuniper.</hi>
                  </hi> Yea, <hi>Pſal. <hi>101.5. Such ſhall be cut off.</hi>
                  </hi> Yet armed with Ale, they euapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate that ſuch and ſuch are miſerable, becauſe they are fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and to better vſes liberall (not haunting nor deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with Drunkards.) Younglings hearing this, ſpend till their purſes be pennileſſe: For a falſe tale with Ale, is in ſtéede of a toaſt. They harken to the fiction: of ſuch is made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, <hi>wherin they thinke it ſtrange, that you run not with them to the ſame exceſſe of ryot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpeaking euil of you.</hi> So ſuch kiſſers of <hi>Culigna</hi> freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exceſſe &amp; riot, and contemne thoſe that wil not. Quaffing mockers <hi>confabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>petulancie</hi> againſt painfull Preachers, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce pomps &amp; vanities, &amp; are induſtrious to draw vs to goodnes, by their good conuerſation, &amp; profitable preaching: which doe pray, watch, and ſtudie, to deliuer Doctrine in the beſt manner, to ſend ſoules to ſaluation: but intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancie vſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, &amp; will not behold the liues of good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <hi>Aſmodeus</hi> do ſpight and not delight them. If any did prooue a ply pot, ready to riot, they would count him quiet, though a pleaſurable plague.</p>
               <p>If Drunkards could draw any to bée as <hi>Simon magus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wong the Diſciples, <hi>and as vnſatiable <hi>Iudas</hi>
                  </hi> among the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Or to refraine from the counſell of <hi>Saint Peter. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt: <hi>5.</hi>
                  </hi> and from the life of <hi>Timoth: <hi>2.</hi> epiſt: <hi>3.10.</hi>
                  </hi> and from the charge giuen him, <hi>2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4;</hi> Sathan had his ſeeking. Or to forget the great menacing: <hi>Ezechiel, <hi>3.18.</hi>
                  </hi> and Chapter. <hi>33.6.</hi> that bloud might goe with bloud, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction for want of inſtructing. Or to be like the trée <hi>Capriſicus,</hi> that God might reiect them. Or aduerſe, to ayme at the vertuous, and quench god beginnes, the Pope, were eaſed, and the Diuell pleaſed. Good men are prudent and innocent, and haue Gods bleſſing, by preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19017:10"/> euill occaſions: for Inticers flatter them in the face; but prate in priuate. The Scorpion hath a fayre face, and a foule tayle: ſo ſome haue ſugred words, but bite the backe. They cannot abide reproouers of impiety; but are like the rude rout which ſaid of <hi>Paul: Act. 22.22. Away with ſuch a fellow from the earth; for it is not fit that hee ſhould liue.</hi> Many quaffers haue ſuch Iewiſh qualities. There can bée no true concord betwéene men moderate, and Monſters inordinate: good and euill agrée not. <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> Enmitie is betwéene the Serpents ſéede and the Womans.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7.</note> Iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> was vexed with the filthy conuerſation of the wicked: but they were deſtroyed, and he was deliuered. The Bée hath honey on her legges, but a ſting in her tayle: ſo, though ſinne ſeemeth ſwéete, when God doth ſtrike the ſtroke, the ſting ſhall ſtrike the ſoule. If ſuch were ſaid to; Leaue hibbing, your houſes and a burning, they would not grudge to haſte home: much leſſe muſt ſuch bee angry, but faſter runne, being warned from exceſſe, that their ſoules be not burned. Alas, men runne to ruine. <hi>It is of the Lords mercies that wee are not conſumed.</hi> To him be all honour for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Laudate Deum.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A profitable Preparatiue for the Exceſſiue.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Beſéech all ſuch as would haue happineſſe, to leaue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and ſeeke for ſafetie, that they may arriue at the Hauen of Heauen: to that purpoſe I expreſſe a Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue as a meanes to bring the body in ſubiection to the ſpirit. It is a Faſting ioyned with true Prayer, not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to merite, as ſond Papiſts affirme, <hi>Luke 17.10. When yee ſhall haue done all thoſe things which are commanded you, ſay, We are vnprofitable ſeruants.</hi> Of Faſting, we read, <hi>Leuit. 23.14.27.29. Iudges 20.26. Daniel 9.3. Ioel 2. Ionas 3. Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> faſted. <hi>Ezra</hi> did appoint it, <hi>8.21. Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſa. 35.13.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19017:11"/> I humbled my ſelfe with faſting.</hi> As it is commanded, ſo it is commended, and of Chriſt and his true ſeruants hath been vſed, <hi>Lu. 4. Acts 9. Acts 10. Acts 13. 1. Cor. 7. 2. Cor. 11. <hi>Omnis Christi actio noſtra eſt inſtructio:</hi> Euery action of Chriſt is our inſtruction.</hi> When hee had caſt a Diuell out of a childe, he ſayd, <hi>Mathew 17; Howbeit, this kinde goeth not out but by Prayer and Faſting.</hi> This might excite vs to Faſt and Pray, it is requiſite and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Anna, a Widdow, departed not from the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but ſerued God with faſtings and prayers.</hi> The exceſſiue ſerue Sathan in feaſting and playing, and gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondize their guts in gluttony. Bee prepared for thy profite, accomodate thy ſelfe fit for fruits of faith; for faſting is a meanes to helpe forward the vertues and graces of the minde. Enter thy chamber, remember what thou art; a blaſt of breath: how ſhort thy time is; not ſure of an houre: and when thou dyeſt, thou goeſt to him thou ſerueſt. <hi>Hilarion</hi> giues vs a leſſon, as <hi>Hierom</hi> relateth; <hi>Ego (Aſine) faciam, te vt non calcitres: <hi>O thou Aſſe</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaid <hi>Hilarion</hi> to his body) <hi>I will make thee that thou kicke not:</hi> meaning, to tame it. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was minded ſo to ſubdue it, <hi>1. Cor. 9.27.</hi> Faſting is a meanes to humble men, and to brydle their affections. <hi>2. Cor. 5.17. If any man be in Chriſt hee is a new creature:</hi> the minde is changed, actions altered, euill company auoyded. Not to drinke betweene meales is profitable and peaceable for people that labour little. If worke requires it, drinke not ſo ſtrong as ſhall make thee ſtagger; rather vſe ſmall Ale, and better Meate.</p>
               <p>Loyterers neede not drinke as Labourers. If wantons would be warned, they might finde it a meanes to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, ſobrietie, lenytie, chaſtitie, health, wit, and wealth: then would they conſider that abſtinence is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and exceſſe needleſſe.</p>
               <p>Some will not faſt truely, becauſe Papiſts faſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and refuſe many good meanes, which others vſe to no
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19017:11"/> good end. Wee ought to faſt, Gods word requires it: our gratious King commands it: our bodies ſhall be the more obedient to the ſpirit, and more ſpared for the poore: which not to regard, is a defect of charitie, no effect of faith, but of infidelitie.</p>
               <p>The ſinne of Sodome was, <hi>Pride, fulneſſe of bread,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eze.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>abundance of idleneſſe, neglect of the needy;</hi> which ſinnes abounde. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Luke 6.25. Woe vnto you that are full; for yee ſhall hunger. Woe vnto you that laugh now; for yee ſhall mourne and weepe.</hi> One ſaith; <hi>Foelicitas &amp; moderatio diuiduum contubernium habent: <hi>Proſperitie and moderation dwell in two houſes.</hi>
                  </hi> It is dainty to finde them dwelling together. Saint <hi>Iames 5.</hi> threatneth the wicked rich men; <hi>Goe to now, ye rich men, weepe and howle for your miſeries that ſhall come vpon you. verſ. 5. Yee haue liued in pleaſure on the earth, and beene wanton: yee haue nouriſhed your hearts, as in a day of ſlaughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſuch could conſider of this, and that thouſands mourne for meate and drinke, which they haue too much of: their pleaſure, would bee pitty: their wantonneſſe, weeping: their feaſting, faſting: which ſurfeting pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents: for it is rare for ſuch as pamper their paunches, to ouercome euill affections. Therefore I pray you vſe this preparatiue. And the peace of God be with vs, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Halelu-iah.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A Letter to the Licentious.</head>
               <p>GRace and peace be with vs. I pray you conſider why impietie is reprooued. The finall cauſe is, that God may bee glorified: for the ſonne that loues his father, grieues to ſee him diſhonoured. The materiall cauſe is the commaundement from God: the efficient in this manner formall: <hi>Leuiticus 19.17. Thou ſhalt not hate thy brother in thy heart: thou ſhalt in any wiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19017:12"/> rebuke thy neighbour, and not ſuffer ſinne vpon him, Heb. 3.13. Exhort one another dayly, 1. Pet. 4. As e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man hath receiued the gift, euen ſo miniſter the ſame one to another.</hi> A good conſcience procures it, and amitie bindes it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Let him know, that he which conuerteth the ſinner from the error of his way, ſhall ſaue a ſoule from death, and ſhall hide a multitude of ſinnes.</hi> Wee ought to ſuccour each other. Commiſeration is a pulſiue cauſe, which mooueth Gods children: They grieue to ſée a Beare teare a childe; much more to ſée Sathan deuoure ſoules. If we ſée a houſe ready to fall on a man, and not aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe him, we are guilty of his death: ſo, if we ſée one ſéeke the detriment of his ſoule, and not admoniſh him, we are culpable.</p>
               <p>Thinke on this, Maſters of families, Victualers, Keepers of Tauerns, and all others; godly zeale exciteth vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12.</note> and God commandeth vs to doe <hi>as we would be done vnto.</hi> And good people doe deſire to bee taught: the bad, like the Diuell, drawes others to euill; and boaſt, they ſhall to heauen; but will not tread the ſtrict path. Oh, it is vnpleaſant: but being profitable, let vs with lenitie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh each other, and deſire to be admoniſhed. A bleſſing is promiſed, <hi>They that turne many to righteouſnes ſhall ſhine as the ſtarres for euer and euer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.</note> He meaneth faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Miniſters, and others of the faithfull: the which hope of felicitie doe quicken to vinification. They indeauour to doe good, and are grieued that the greedy Diuell gets many into his net. It is furniſhed with leawd delights, alluring baytes, and ſugred ſinnes. If a Calumnor take his part to confront my labour, I wiſh him, firſt to conſider; Satan doth couſen him, to hale him to hell; I doe counſell him, and haſte him to heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Eſchew the Diuels net full of falſe bayts.</head>
               <p>PArtialitie, for the careleſſe Officer: ſuperfluous ſpeach, for Buyers and Sellers: euill excuſe, for Swearers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19017:12"/> and Lyers: falſe hope to eſcape, for the Théefe and Filcher: falſe hope of gaine, for the Dicer and Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: néedleſſe breake, for the baſe Bankrout: calliditie for the Couſener, which for fauour will lye, and ſay he is a kinne to good men. Infidelitie for the Atheiſt: bragge boldneſſe for the Blaſphemer: wilfulnes, for the Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: enuy, for the Ambitions: reuenge, for Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. Murther, for the Wrathfull. Lone of loathſome luſt, for Drunkards, Gluttons, and filthy Fornicators. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate loue of the carcaſſe, for the proud and painted. Gryping gaine, for Vſurers and greedy Extortioners. Worldly affection, for the couetous. Cruelty for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull. Deſperation and deſtruction, for the faithleſſe. Diſdaine of Gods word, for negligent hearers. No regard of God, for riotous Royſters. Diſſimulation, for <hi>Iudas</hi>-like hypocrites. Vaine-glory, for pickthankly world-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers. Deceipt, for ſeducers. Carnall pleaſures, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane liuers. Hate of truth, for Sectaries. Deſire to get, for the Empericke, which by vnſkilfulnes cauſeth death or long ſickneſſe. Enticings to all euil, haſtinge from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, halings to hell. Many looke like <hi>Lucifer</hi> to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with the quiot: but cowards to reſiſt Sathan; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers them, &amp; ſnarls them in his ſnares to torment them euer. To preuent it, repent, pray for a cleare heart, and a right ſpirit, reſt not till you haue it: abandon the déedes of the fleſh, imbrace the fruits of the ſpirit;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>They that are Chriſts haue crucified the fleſh, with the affections and luſts.</hi> With faith and amendment apprehend Chriſts merits, then God will behold thee in him, thou ſhalt haue fauour with our heauenly Father. Conſider my Letter: and the Lord aſſiſt vs. Abhorre Sathans ſnares. <hi>Iam. 4. Reſiſt the Diuell, and hee will flye from you: draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you.</hi> With a <hi>Memento:</hi> Imbrace amendment, haue it <hi>in ſempiternam rei memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam. Sic fiat.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Rocede à malo, &amp; fac bonum.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19017:13"/>
               <head>¶ Reproofe of Whoredome, a collaterall conſort to exceſſe, attendant to the ſame.</head>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sublata cauſa tollitur effectus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Take away the cauſe, and the effect falleth.</l>
               </q>
               <p>QVaffing is ſo accuſtomable, that Whoredome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is the ſequel; ſo monſterous, as, to auoyd long period; I will not expreſſe. Much youth betimes fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Fornication; the which <hi>coition</hi> is execrable. <hi>1. Cor. 6.9.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A reproofe of Fornication.</note> 
                  <hi>No Fornicator ſhall inherit the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. verſ. 18. Flee fornication: euery ſinne that a man doth, is without the body: but he that committeth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, ſinneth againſt his owne body.</hi> He defileth his owne ſoule and body, and alſo the party with whom he is ſo filthy. Thinkeſt thou to make amends with mariege? repent, remember the dreadfull ſentence, <hi>Reuel. 22. Such ſhall be ſhut out from heauen. Eph. 5.3. Fornication and vncleaneneſſe muſt not bee once named.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>For this is the will of God, euen your ſanctification, that ye ſhould abſtaine from fornication.</hi> It is ſo heynous, and God doth ſo abhorre it: <hi>1. Cor. 10.8. that there fell in one day three and twenty thouſand.</hi> Conſider this, ye ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les fornicators, with dogs and bitches qualities, your ſins cry for vengeance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.13.</note> as the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome. Re. 14. It is written that no man could learn that new ſong, but they which were not defiled with women; for they are virgins.</hi> And would you ſing in heauen? repent leſt ye ſigh in hell. Young men &amp; maydens, if ſinners intice you, conſent not: take example of chaſte <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An example for youth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.8.</note> when he was offerrd, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed; for he feard God. <hi>The body is not for fornication, but for the Lord:</hi> yet ſuch forſake Chriſt; and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the members of an harlot. They are repugnant to thoſe that kéepe themſelues chaſte for the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſake, which Chriſt hath ſet in a place of price, and ſaith, <hi>Mat. 19. Hee that can take it, let him take it:</hi> but a varlet takes an harlot. Hee that hath not the gift to liue
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19017:13"/> ſingle and chaſt, may ſéeke for mariage, lawful for all men:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.4.</note> and is an <hi>Antidotarie</hi> againſt fornication, to bee vſed in the feare of God, for the procreation of children, and for the mutuall ſocietie of each other.</p>
               <p>Yet many of the ſauadge ſort maryed know not the right vſe of mariage, but linger after luſts like bruit beaſts, and like a <hi>Nicholaitan,</hi> not content, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proud Paramour. The vnmaried &amp; maried of leawd diſpoſition muſt be aduertiſed by <hi>Solomon; Pro. 23.27.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A reproofe of Adultery.</note> 
                  <hi>A whore is a deepe ditch, and a ſtrange woman is a narrow pit. Pro. 6. He that committeth adultery, deſtroyeth his owne ſoule. Her houſe inclyneth vnto death, &amp; her paths vnto the dead. None that go to her returne againe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take they hold of the waies of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh drudges of drudgery, ye refuſe the heauenly felicity. <hi>Adultery, fornication, vncleannes, laciuiouſnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. All kinde of vnleanneſſe muſt be aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned. <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113. <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. <hi>Amos</hi> 9. A meanes of chaſtitie.</note> are fruits of the fleſh, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitters thereof ſhal not inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. It is to be feared, that fornicators &amp; adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers are Atheiſts: for durſt any doe ſuch a thing before a king? they doe it before the All-ſeeing King of kings. <hi>The eyes of the Lord are in euery place, beholding the euill &amp; the good.</hi> Yet <hi>Aſotus</hi> ſerues <hi>Aſmodeus,</hi> in Cities, towns, and countries. <hi>Pſa. 97. Ye that loue the Lord, hate euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A meanes of chaſtity is mediocrity in dyet, labor, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, prayer, reading, hearing &amp; meditating: refrayning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ton co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, vnchaſt ſpeaches, gawiſh apparrel, gazing on the diſguiſed, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wanton looks: therfore rule thy row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eies. Iuſt <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>31. I made a couenant with mine eies, why ſhould I think vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a maid?</hi> If thy heart be cleane thy eye is ruled; if thy heart be wicked, thy eye is wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring, which fils thy hart ful of pollution. Chriſt faith, <hi>Mat. 5.28. Whoſoeuer looketh on a woman,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28.</note> 
                  <hi>to luſt after her hath committed adultery with her already in his heart.</hi> Kéepe in thy eye, the heart will be the better, vſe it to thy booke. <hi>2. Sam. 11. Dauid</hi> looked on the wife of <hi>Vriah;</hi> hee liked, luſted, and for it was perplexed: and hauing a new heart,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19017:14"/> hee prayeth to the Lord, <hi>Pſa. 119.37. Turne away mine eyes from beholding vanitie. Gen. 12. Pharaoh was plagued,</hi> and all his houſe, with great plagues for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in <hi>Sara,</hi> vnknowne to them to be a wife. Yee Luſt-louers, leaue it. Yée Fornicators and Adulterers, in pretence and action, how ſhall ye eſcape the vengeance to come? your idleneſſe and drunkenneſſe bringeth Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards. I grudge not your collections, but grieue at your ſmall corrections. Oh, <hi>Salax,</hi> bee ſanctified, reſiſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than. <hi>Suſanna</hi> conſented not, but withſtood the ſtout Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Be warned, youth was neuer more wayward.</note>Conſider this, you that are marryed, and are inordinate in abuſing your bed: O feare the Lord, leſt your propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be vntoward, extraordinary and ſtange, abortiue or vntimely. Imitate <hi>Tobias, 8.</hi> He being newly maried to <hi>Sara,</hi> roſe out of the bed, and ſaid, Siſter, ariſe, and let vs pray, that God would haue pitty on vs: and the latter end of his prayer was this; <hi>verſ. 7; And now, ô Lord, I take not this my Siſter for luſt, but vprightly: therefore, mercyfully ordaine that we may become aged together. And ſhe ſaid with him, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </hi> And I pray God more may be ſo minded, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Timete Iehouam.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Starch is here reprooued: Poking-irons are ill vſed.</head>
               <p>AS by Gods word Drunkenneſſe and Whoredome is conuinced: ſo is Starch, made of that which is the chiefeſt foode for the ſuſtentation of vs, here reprooued. For, whereas poore people that want bread ſhould be nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and fed therewith; many, to fulfill their fond affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, feede their great Ruffs; which ſhewes we haue more deſire to carnall delights, then loue to relieue the needy. Many men, women, &amp; children, want bread, which earth doth vſe for pride. But Loue-luſts ſay they buy it, and the efore not culpable of the making; a ridiculous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe: for if there were no buyer, there ſhould be no ſeller.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19017:14"/>
               <p>There be wealthy Houſwiues, and good houſe-kéepers that vſe no ſtarch, but faire water: their Linnen is white, and they looke more Chriſtian-like in ſmall Ruffes, then <hi>Light of loue</hi> lookes in her great ſtarched ruffs; looke ſhe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo hie, with eye-lids awrye.</p>
               <p>The princely Prophet ſaith, <hi>Him that hath an hie looke and a proude heart, will not I ſuffer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> Preſuppoſe prettie pleaſure did ſay: Where finde you in Gods word ſtarch forbidden? It is like it was not vſed in the time of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, therefore not named. But the Diuell hath inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, and many ſuch deuiſes, in theſe laſt luſtfull dayes.</p>
               <p>I finde that <hi>CHRIST</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whatſoeuer yee would that men ſhould doe to you, euen ſo doe you to them.</hi> (Therefore conſider) would you the poore ſhuld vſe vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable meanes to make you ſuffer hunger and colde? No,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math:</hi> 7.12</note> no, pricked pride, your fruits are faultie. <hi>Whatſoeuer will ſerue neceſſarily for the ſuſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation of man, ought not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably to be ſpent: but</hi> the Meale, <hi>Starch is made of, will ſerue neceſſarily for the ſuſtentation of man. <hi>Ergò,</hi> it ought not vnprofitably to be ſpent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> conſiſteth of no falſe principles. And if you think it not ſpent vnprofitably vpon great ruffs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the effects. Firſt, it hindreth our food:<note place="margin">Diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſtarch, &amp; ſtarching.</note> it waſteth our wood, it ſpends the precious <hi>Time,</hi> that might be ſpent bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And people liue gréedily, and néedily, to maintaine it. It frets out much Linnen, and the poking-Irons ſeare it: and waſting that people want (it is to be feared) it hath often moued <hi>GOD</hi> to ſeare the Corne and Graſſe vpon the ground.</p>
               <p>Wanton wenches are tempters and Inticers, that ruffs muſt be great, and ſtarched. Good men muſt reſiſt them; for <hi>Eue</hi> by inticing, brought <hi>Adam</hi> to ruine. There is as much ſpent in that haynous order, as might ſuſtaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie poore people which aſke <hi>Bread;</hi> The anſwer is, I haue it not; when <hi>Newe-guiſe</hi> hath it about the necke. Manie ſpend Daies and Nights vnprofitably to ſet great Ruffs,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19017:15"/> yea oft when they ſhould heare and learne Gods word.</p>
               <p>Oh ſhameleſſe Mares, more liker then baſhfull Maids, that ſpend moſt parte of theyr life time about Starch and ſtarching, patting, pulling, thruſting, rubbing, wearing, tearing, and ſtarching of cloth with hote Irons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucifer</hi> inuenter of Pride hath inuented an exerciſe, wherein <hi>Minion Meretrix</hi> takes alacritie. Much wood is ſpent friuolouſly, and the poore vnable to buy it. Much lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen by them is burnt, and the Poore want cloth to ſhifte them. Starch is taken from wheate Meale, and many crie out for courſe crible. Yet fancie fine, with ruffes vp to her eyne, likes not to be reprooued. To cull and kiſſe, her pleaſure it is, ſay what you will.</p>
               <p>I ſay the poking irons whereby they deſtroy good ſtuffe, is méeter for a Plummer, and puniſhment méet for Pride. Oh careleſſe Caterpillers, that ſpend vp peoples Foode, for the leaude luſts of theyr hearts! How can you anſwere it before GOD?</p>
               <p>Excuſe ſaith, it ſhewes cleaner the longer. I anſwer, it is rotted the ſooner. (And further) twiſe waſhing is not ſo much labour, as patting and ſtarching. And they that haue bread can waſh oft. But take away the bread, the life is loſt, wherof one is more precious then all ſtarch. And wilt thou be culpable of death by thy great Ruffes? which ſtand ſtiffe, agreable to thy ſtoutnes. Be not a beaſt bolde and paſt ſhame, to doe ſuch hurt by thy hauty heart. Set not out thy great Ruffs, as though thou wouldſt take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy flight with <hi>Icarus.</hi> It is a meanes to make thée loue the luſtes of thy bodie, to looke bigge with ſtiffe-necke, as though thou wert the popes brother, or ſhould marry <hi>Ien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ietter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh earth looke to thy féete: when breath is out, thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is a fearfull Anatomie. But <hi>Salax</hi> loues not to heare of Earth nor Death: the excuſe is, ſtarch is made of bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. If ſo, good for Horſes, and other good vſes, to ſuſtaine that which hath life, the more Oates and Peaſe ſhould be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19017:15"/> for the poore, which wiſh to be ſuffiſed with branne, and want it. But it is apparent, it is made of that which may make good bread.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the face of the waters.</hi> But many kéepe it from the poore,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.</note> and caſt it on great Ruffs. <hi>Salomon</hi> vſeth an Ironie, and ſaith, <hi>reioyce.</hi> Then he ſhewes the ignominie: that ſuch rude reioycing brings iudgement. Yet ſome that ſo walke in the wayes of their hart, and ſight of their eyes, doe adulate that they are addict vnto: and when white ſtarch is ſtale, then they vſe yellow, or blue, &amp; know not how ſoone to taſte of gréene among wormes, or of blue Brimſtone in deſtruction. Be warned, thy time is ſhort. Pray that thine eyes may be opened: to that end I write to leaud life that walks in the broad-way, as moſt people run from Heauen to <hi>Gehenna.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The cauſe of Couſening, Dearth, and Scarcitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VOrax,</hi> deuouring of much, yet grudging. The more ſuch get, the more they want; they gape with guile, yet haue they ſcant. Riot, bibbing, painted back, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many daily lacke. Bringing Dearth and ſcarcitie, murther whoredome, bribery. Till exceſſe of Belly and Backe be left, all Vices will abound with theft. Turne therefore ſuperfluitie, to meane and mediocritie, and then this Realme to penurie, ſhall not decreaſe by pouertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of abuſe in Apparell.</head>
               <p>IN this reproouing of ſuperfluous Attire, thrée things are to be conſidered. Firſt, the manner of exceſſe. <hi>2.</hi> the euill effects. <hi>3.</hi> the reproofe by Gods word. Concerning the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, I purpoſe to reueale the folly of ſuch as are poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced pompions, dead man like, with all their ſubſtance on their backs. Excéeding wealthy men and matrones which kéepe hoſpitalitie for the hungrie, and are plainely Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, when being ouer-worne, are giuen to the néedy.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19017:16"/> Such refraine from exceſſe, and do ſpare for the poore. But as ſome gormandize their guts, that their backes are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for want of ſhifting: So <hi>Superbia</hi> pincheth the belly, and painteth the Backe, and ieopardeth the beſt ioynte to iet in colors, that mediocritie is excluded from either.</p>
               <p>Wee ought to weare decent Apparell to couer our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: But they which abuſe Gods benefits in cutting Cloth full of flaſhes, makes them vnméet to couer Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or to keepe off colde, or for any good purpoſe for the Poore. As there is Veluet for ſuperiours, ſo Ruſſet fits inferiors: but many of the meaner ſort haue brought cloth to exceſſe price by vndiſcrete waſting, that the poore deplore it. And they beſtowe as much coſt in their capes, cuttes, iagges, lace, &amp; needleſſe Nouelties, as the outſide comes to. Were it not for fond faſhions which we learne from other Nations, famous <hi>Brittaine</hi> ſhould be more famous. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue delight of the carcaſſe, doth digreſſe from our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and is a ſcarre to our true profeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Myriades</hi> of faſhions are followed. It is to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how brag boyes and wenches will paint their bodies. It's to be feared they ſeeke not ſutes for their ſoules. <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat</hi> is arrogant, ſhe hath her <hi>Apologie,</hi> though no other <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, that Pride is not in her Apparell.</hi> I wiſh her to learne this and auoyde it: that Pride is <hi>Matercula &amp; origo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium vitiorum</hi> the mother and nurſe of all miſchiefe, roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the heart, and breaketh foorth as a leaproſie, in obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate words, peruerſe déedes, &amp; outragious Apparell, which are fruites of proude and vaine delighted hearts, that are not wearie of this world, but wedded to it. Such as are proud in rags (had they wherewith) would illuſtrate their pride by Attyre. If any obiect, that it is a ſmall matter, and as Mynte and Anyſéede, in reſpect of greater; Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the effects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Effects of exceſſiue Apparell.</head>
               <p>GOd which forbids it is diſobeyed, and his anger pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured. Many to be <hi>concinnate</hi> and finely apparelled,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19017:16"/> buy, and are truſted. It is pleaſant in buying, but it pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth in the paying. Man and Wife looke awry, and are at contrarietie. Concord decreaſeth, they perſeuer, and are not placable. Their thrift is turnd to ſhift, they part, or liue not in loue. Some prooue Théeues, and whores, by whome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are perplexed, that they apprehend and hang them. Some are ſo hanty they wilbe as braue as the wealthy, and haue it, <hi>quo iure, quàve iniuria,</hi> by hooke or crooke, till at length that is pledged which purchaſeth no honeſtie nor profite.</p>
               <p>Others of pretty wealth (ſeeing that preſumption) ſtep paſt theyr degrée, attired triumphant: So euill is imitated, goodnes neglected. They liue deceitfully, and wickedly, to painte theyr houſes of clay. Some will haue great Ruffes, though hoſe hang out at héeles, and they prooue hackneys. In time paſt one might haue clad himſelfe as cheap as two great Ruffes and ſtarching comes to; many rich painte and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per themſelues. Exceſſe makes one to pine at anothers proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, and both chaſe away true amitie. They want, yet haue too much, they conſume it on theyr luſts, by ſtarch and great ruffes. The world was neuer ſo gréedy, fierce, and full of furie. One couets anothers houſe ouer his head: If <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> were here, he would be enuyed for his tunne. Men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not liue of much; Land and liuing is too little. That which ſhould ſuſtaine the hungrie, is ſpent in prodigalitie, gawiſh Garments, friuolous faſhions, tufts, trifles. People may perceiue by view of Verdigalls, that if ſome had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, their buttocks had bene bigge. Exceſſe of the carcas cauſeth Common-wealth-conſumers, true dealing to be excluded, Senſualitie maintained, the néedy not nouriſhed.</p>
               <p>Much is ſpent in pride, which cauſeth <hi>Dolus</hi> to haue <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</hi> qualities, with face of Auarice and anſtere countenance, to pinch the Poore, the Fatherles, and defraud the Friendles. The proud do preye vpon ſuch. If they miſſe of their purpoſe, they menace and maligne them. God hath forbidden it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal:</hi> 3.5</note> and will be a ſwift witnes againſt ſuch. Yet people procure the heauy curſe, to painte theyr haultie corps.</p>
               <p>Exceſſe of Apparell procures couetouſnes. A Cormorant
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19017:17"/> ſelleth any thing that an other may not owne. Rents are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Bribes imbraced, Timber goeth down, without regard of Nauigation. <hi>Ouidius. Creſcit amor nummi quantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pecunia creſcit: <hi>as thy money increaſeth, ſo doth the loue of it.</hi>
                  </hi> Yet read we, <hi>The couetous hath no inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Burſa auari os eſt diaboli. <hi>The purſe of a couetous man is the mouth of the diuell.</hi>
                  </hi> The eyes of the exceſſiue are like Hell, neuer ſatiſfied, <hi>Tam deest quod habet, quam quod non habet.</hi> He wanteth that he hath, as that he hath not: All is to maintain pride. The body is decked, the ſoule neglected, the Saboth is broken by tricking and trimming meate for maddes. In ſtéed of a Booke to ſée our ſinnes, ſome foote two houres in a glaſſe to frame a frontlet. Ruffs muſt haue <hi>Rebatoes.</hi> If ſhe turne her face, her body turneth, elſe the ruffe is bruſed. So her neck ſtandeth ſtiffe ſtretched, like her ſiſters of <hi>Syon,</hi> and ſhewing her ſhameleſſe labour, ſhe comes to the <hi>Cathedrall,</hi> when Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is halfe done, in time to be ſéene, though not to learne; farre finer then at the doale the day before. She feares no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſting, her huſband is hidden. Exceſſe brought his diſtreſſe. Yet if drinked drop on her great ruffe, a change preſent, ſome ſhall pay for it.</p>
               <p>O Earth, thinke on the fearfull Iudgement ſhewed on a woman in <hi>Antwerpe</hi> (as it is related) to whome the diuell appeared to ſet her Ruffs, which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had finiſhed, he kiſſed her, &amp; wroong her necke in twoo. Her bodie ſuddenly changed blacke and blewe, painted and coloured ſmall to her profite. Laid in a toumbe, ſhe was ſuddenly gone, and a blacke defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Cat in the roome. If curious <hi>Ruff-mongers,</hi> be incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of this, I wiſh them beware, leaſt to them come the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 12.</note>Gay Attyre is a meanes to pull the minde from heauen. <hi>Herode</hi> in his Royall Apparell, vnmindefull of God, was ſmitten of the Angell. The attire of the Daughters of <hi>Syon,</hi> procured the ſworde.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Iezabel</hi> preſently after her Attyring and painting had paine. Many procure theyr pouertie and paine; Fellowes prophane, conſume theyr ſubſtance to pleaſe theyr Paramours. Oh yée that are ouercome by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> rather by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enerie,</hi> be not led by ignorant, arrogant wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19017:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> whoſe wanton attyre bewrayes a Harlots heart, I am painted to play with.</p>
               <p>Oh Worme for wormes, thy carcas ſhall be Carren: thou haſt prickes in thy forehead, be prickt with repentance. O <hi>Salax</hi> be ſanctified, be clothed with Sobrietie, repent with Fidelitie. Remember thy winding ſhéete: when that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, thy carcas ſhalbe naked.<note place="margin">Coſeners are Theeues, as waſps among Bees.</note> Doe not for inordinate loue thereof, vndoe thy ſelfe. Following faſhions procures bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, and chaſeth brotherly ſocietie. Some braue, doe brag they are of hability. So get they goods in credite, but flée in falſhood. Others to allure, like the Harlot.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou:</hi> 7.</note> The <hi>Leopard</hi> by his ſpotted ſkinne inticeth Beaſts and killeth them. His ſkinne is good, his fleſh is naught. So Sepulchers are pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet full of putrefaction. Fine are ſome outſides, as if the inſides were anſwerable, it ſmelleth of Hypocriſie, we are full of corruption.</p>
               <p>It was the ſaying of an Emperour, Sumptuouſnes of Apparel is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>exillum ſuperbiae, Nidus Luxuria: <hi>The Banner of Pride, the neſt of Luſt.</hi> Herodotus</hi> writeth in his Booke, that <hi>Iuda Dictator</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> had a Sonne, being prickt vp in gay apparell, had no minde of his book, but delighted in pride, &amp; at length was hanged, as many are in theſe dayes, whoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents farre inferior deck their bodies, and neglect their ſoules; which makes them ſo hautie, that their Hattes are heauie in preſence of Magiſtracie: Pride makes them forget the God of might, to whom be all honour for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Superna curate.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Exceſſe of Apparell reprooued,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. <hi>Paule</hi>
                  </hi> willeth that Women adorne themſelues in modeſt apparell, with ſhamefaſtnes and ſobrietie. Whereby we muſt learne that modeſt apparell ſiſter in equalitie to ſhamefaſtnes and ſobrietie, doth more adorne and beautifie. But the contraries are common. Immodeſt apparell out of meaſure, boldneſſe and light behauiour. A Garment is fitteſt to modeſtie, voyde of ſuperfluitie. Who goe more in gaudes then great mens Idiotes? Yet many imitate the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19017:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſame, with néedleſſe vanities and tokens of wantonneſſe. Exceſſe is ſo in vſe, that ſhamefaſtnes and modeſtie with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie are abſent, when Curioſitie, gay Tufts, great Ruffs, ſtiffe Necks, Stout-looke, with ſmall Grace, is preſent. Bold as a Bull, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tokens of diſhoneſty, bluſhing no more then a beaſt.</p>
               <p>The holy Ghoſt fordiddeth <hi>Broydered haire, or golde, or pearles, or coſtly Aray.</hi> Some ſay, <hi>It is not coſtly, ſo long as they can maintaine it.</hi> Conſider, <hi>The Lorde threatned to puniſh the Princes and the Kings children, and all, ſuch as are clothed with ſtrange Apparell.</hi> Much more ought <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnata</hi> to feare,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zephan:</hi> 1.8,</note> which is poore, yet pompous.</p>
               <p>We muſt not clad clay to the outmoſt of abilitie, but learne the Apoſtles meaning; for golde, pearles, and coſtly Aray is not only forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo broided haire (which is not coſtly) but plaited, buſhed, or laid out: wherby all po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p &amp; prouocations to euill is forbidden) which wanton women procure, in dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelues. For it is is a meanes to drawe the heart to delight the bodie, and leaude pleaſures thereof, the World, and vanities thereof, to renounce Gods Kingdome, and the Ioyes thereof, to haue Hell and the torments thereof. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch vanitie is forbidden, and the habite agreable to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, ſhamefaſtnes, and ſobrietie commanded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke was pitched without and within: So the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward habit muſt be as the humble hart, &amp; our harts muſt be reformed, elſe our actions are abhorred. <hi>1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 3. Whoſe adorning let it not bee that outward, of plaiting the haire, and of wearing of golde, or of putting on of Apparell.</hi> It requires the Ornament of a méeke and quiet ſpirite, as holie men which truſted in God adorned themſelues. <hi>Cap: <hi>5.</hi>
                  </hi> He bids them be clothed with humilitie; <hi>For <hi>GOD</hi> reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.</hi> But many are clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with haughtines, as if pleaſures were their God.</p>
               <p>The <hi>7.</hi> commandement is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultry:</hi> which is to be vnderſtood, the euill acte, and prouocations; as vnchaſt behauiour,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 5.</note> wanton apparell. <hi>Abſtain from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of euill:</hi> That hath any ſhewe of euill. It is written <hi>Deut: <hi>22.5. The woman ſhall not weare that which partai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19017:18"/> vnto a man, neither ſhall a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put on a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſeemes a ſmall matter: ſo did it to <hi>Eue,</hi> to taſte for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit. Oh fooliſh fleſh! it followes: <hi>for all that doe ſo, are abhomination vnto the Lord thy God.</hi> It ſeemes ſome care not to be abhorred of God, they will be as fine as <hi>D.</hi> in their Dubblets, liker men, then women: wanton apparell is forbidden, <hi>verſ <hi>11. Thou ſhalt not weare a garment of diuers ſorts, as of Wollen, and Linnen together:</hi>
                  </hi> but where the luſts of the fleſh are delighted, God is not regarded: for ſome at Font for faſhion, vowe to him that they forſake the Deuill and all his workes, the vaine pompe and glory of the world, tha carnall deſires of the fleſh, and that they will not follow nor be led by them, yet painted for a Play, ruft like a royſter. Some that haue hayre of their owne are not content with the colour God gaue it, but weare hayre none of their owne. Others launch out their hayre dyed a Trim-tawny: then muſt be muſke, to preuent the ſent: ſo perſeuering in wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton behauiour they breake their fidelitie and couenant made with God, promiſe in Baptiſme is forgotten. Oh be not hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, but Chriſtians in déede: promiſes to men muſt be perfomed, <hi>Pſal. 15.</hi> much more vowes made to God. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your vanities, follow righteouſneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.11 <hi>Deu.</hi> 23.21</note> 
                  <hi>leſt yee feele your folly, Eſa. 3. The Lord ſaith, becauſe the daughters of Zion are hautie, and walke with ſtretched forth neckes, and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they goe, and making a tinkling with their feet:</hi> he would take away their braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and giue them in ſtéed of well ſet hayre, baldneſſe; which came to paſſe with much miſerie.</p>
               <p>You with great Ruffes, and ſtretched neckes, leaue it: when pride is at the higheſt, it is neereſt the fall, <hi>2 Kings 9. Iezabel</hi> painted her face, and attired her head, but preſently trodden vnder feet, and torne with Dogges: yet painting and making the face ſhine like a ſhoing-horne, is common.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui ſe pingunt in hoc ſeculo, aliter quam creauit Deus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
                  <hi>metuant ne cum dies reſurrectionis venerit, artifex creaturam ſuam non recognoſcat.</hi> Thoſe which paint or colour themſelues in this world otherwiſe then God hath made them, let them feare,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19017:19"/> leſt when the day of Iudgement commeth, the Lord will not know them for his creatures. Some will haue their beauty decored, it is to be feared their ſoules are deformed. And as their ſoules are alienated and eſtranged, ſo their bodies are metamorphoſed, and changed from the faſhion God framed them.</p>
               <p>Exornation hath no order: Many make themſelues ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-ſtockes till they proue poore, and are kept on the Pariſh, <hi>Prou. 7.</hi> She that inticed the young man was clothed in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots attire; whereby we gather by the holy Ghoſt, that intin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing attyre is whoriſh, <hi>Tit. 2.</hi> Temperance is an adiunct to Chriſtians: if <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> had continued in their firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, garments had beene néedleſſe: and ſhall we extoll our ſelues in that which our perfidious act procured? Will a Théefe gild the rope his théeuiſh act hath purchaſed? If a <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pronian</hi> ſay: The rope bereft the life, but apparell preſerues the ſame: I ſay, coſtly array which is by Gods word forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, is a meanes to kill Body and Soule, <hi>Prou. 3.5. Leane not vnto thine owne vnderſtanding:</hi> the leaſt ſinne deſerues damnation; yet we forſake heauenly directions, and follow fleſhly affections. <hi>Suus cuiuſque crepitus, ſibi bene olet:</hi> euery one thinketh his owne wayes beſt. O be not wey-ward, but warned, for the holy Ghoſt ſpeakes not in vaine. God made <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> coates of ſkinnes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.21.</note> and cloathed them; yet they had the ſuperioritie of the whole Earth. Therefore this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared apparell for them ſhould be as a glaſſe to vs, to ſée and flye from Folly: and a <hi>Pedagogie</hi> to teach vs to vſe it for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, not for ſenſualitie.</p>
               <p>But how agrée the comely coates of theſe wealthy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, with the ſuperfluous faſhions of <hi>Wat Waſte-all.</hi> and fooleries of Minion Marre-all, which goe paſt their abilitie, ſhameleſſe and graceleſſe with all their wealth in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to be viewed? And how agreeth fancy fine nobles, with iagges, welts, gardes, gay tufts, great Rufs, confuſed ſets, ſupporters, buſhes to make their bodies ſtraight, and want of Gods word to rule their ſoules right? their corked héeles ſet vp ſo hie, that ſome doe tread awry. They deſpiſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19017:19"/> and didiget at thoſe that weare ſmall Bands, and plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent apparell, which are worne for foure cauſes. Firſt, to be obedient to God, and agreeable to his word. Secondly, for a helpe to pull downe our pride. Thirdly, to win others. Fourthly, they maintaine it with trueth and honeſtie. Boe aſhamed you and yours, that conſume all by your exceſſe.</p>
               <p>Pride is combined with witleſſe faſhions: Some men are like monſters, with Ruffes, farre excéeding former Ruffins: Boyes haue ſhalt haired heads; ſome bigger, a curious cut; lockes for <hi>pediculus,</hi> long of each ſide, <hi>ſtigmaticall like.</hi> He that ſubiected his body, ſaith: <hi>Doth not euen Nature it ſelfe teach you, that if a man haue long hayre it is a ſhame vnto him? 1 Cor. 11. <hi>Nitimur in vetitum ſemper, cupimuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> negata.</hi>
                  </hi> We deſire things forbid, and couet things denyed vs. Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh pompe, and Spaniards pride hath long lockes, as if they were aſhamed of their eares; with Shirts hanging out at knees, diſguiſed from top to toe, as if they went to the pit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall.</p>
               <p>A mans attire, and exceſſiue laughter and gate,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 19.30.</note> ſhew what he is. <hi>Ambr. <hi>1.</hi> Officior. Eſt in ipſo motu, geſtu, &amp; inceſſu te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda verecundia: habitus enim animi in corporis ſtatu cognoſcitur.</hi> Externall actions bewraye internall affections: ſome excéed in varietie as though they might ſpend much a yere by Land, yet nothing. Men of Nobilitie, Gentilitie, and Yeomen of habilitie goe decent and plaine, when farre inferiours are ſhin-trim, and garded with others goods got by guile. O earth be humble, <hi>Gen. 2.7.</hi> thou wert made of that beaſts tread vpon, <hi>Gen. 3.14.</hi> and of that Serpents eate on. Our firſt Parents were Gods Vicegerents, and God could as eaſily haue cloathed them in gorgeous apparrell as in plaine coates of ſkinnes. Then minde it, it was to mooue vs to mediocritie.</p>
               <p>Thoſe garmenes ſpeake to vs that GOD allowes vs cloths to couer our nakednes, but not to abuſe them in exceſſe. Chriſt nor his Apoſtles gaue no ſuch examples: <hi>Chriſts gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was without ſeame. Math. 3. Iohn</hi> had his rayment
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19017:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> of Camels hayre, and a leathern pelt about his loynes. Gods children haue beene content to weare ſheepes ſkinnes, and Goates ſkinnes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37.</note> Garments according to euery mans calling, plaine and comely, are commendable: we may vſe them, but not abuſe them. It is lawfull to eate, drinke, and weare ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell: but exceſſe of eyther incurres Gods diſpleaſure. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>food and raiment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>let vs therewith be content.</hi> It is more then God owes vs, and wee (proud beggars) deſerue nothing but damnation. Content muſt be when wee haue but food and rayment: if riches, wee muſt not conſume them on our luſts: If a Ruffin ſay that he and his doe vſe exceſſe to pleaſe his Wife, he is not fit to rule a houſeholde, and vnlike the good Centurion, to ſay, <hi>Doe this, and it is done.</hi> Saith <hi>Ioſua, 24.15. As for me, and my houſehold, wee will ſerue the Lord.</hi> Pray that ſhe which allures thée, and oft rules thee, be not a let like <hi>Eue,</hi> but a helpe as <hi>Sara:</hi> not ſauadge, but ſage. <hi>Pro. 31. The price of the vertuous is farre aboue Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies.</hi> If ſhe be ſuch, ſo is thy houſehold, prayſe God for her; if ſhe be not, pray God to conuert her. Be not <hi>Cynicus,</hi> ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuffer ſorrow: admoniſh her quietly, loue her, and winne her with lenitie. If ſhée ſee that you gréeue indéed, that ſhée offend God by her exceſſiue attire, ſhe cannot loue thee and vſe it, but leaue it if ſhe loue thée. Loue God and leaue it, hee forbids it: it is an offence to Gods children, whom hee hath ſuch care of, that it were better for their offender, <hi>that a Mill ſtone were hanged about his necke, and that hee were drowned in the depth of the Sea, Math. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</note> Some lawfull thing to auoyd offence is to be omitted: much more vnlawfull, as ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. And who dare diſobey Gods word? except ſuch as in heart haue him not: his word is ſufficient to conuince: yet the ſayings of the <hi>Painims</hi> incomparable in efficacie to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Diuinity may be expreſſed, becauſe their careful doings excell careleſſe Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Monta.</note>Hate pride, deſire to be cleanly, not gorgeous in apparell: Hee toucheth the Momes, not men, which ſpend all at the Ale-houſe till hare ſkin appeares: and dirtie (not deyrie) wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which launch their hayre out long, and leaue it in whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meat.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19017:20"/>
               <p>Oh foole, gorgeous apparrell is not an Ornament,<note place="margin">Sophocles.</note> but a ſhame, and manifeſt ſhew of thy folly. Hee toucheth thoſe that would be extolled, but haue ſhame in ſtead of fame: for Ruffians ſpeake raſhly of their diſhoneſty.</p>
               <p>Gay apparrelled women ſtand foorth as bayts to catch men. Hee toucheth the diſguiſed with fore-heads frizled,<note place="margin">Aurelius.</note> which buye Complexion, and cauſe an euill action ſtanding more bold then baſhfull, painted to play with.</p>
               <p>The women of <hi>Lacedemon</hi> refuſed the rich Roabes King <hi>Dioniſius</hi> ſent them, ſaying they would do them more ſhame then honour. If ſuch were now offered, ſtretched out armes would reach them, and gréedy <hi>Geheſa</hi> would haue them.</p>
               <p>Some ſo delight the fleſh, that good ſayings nor examples doe not amend their miſdoings. <hi>Demas</hi> forſaketh the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly conuerſation of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and imbraceth this preſent world: (the Vipers garled ſkinne, whoſe venemous ſting is deadly.) Oh eleuate thy heart to heauen:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let vs examine our ſelues: Doth the Spirit of Chriſt, which is alwaies in ſharpe and painefull battels with the fleſh, and locked in that dungeon of dung, delight to ſet out, the ſame in exceſſe? No, for it is a meanes of carnall deſires: it hath reſpect to the ſoule, by whom the body liueth. It al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the body that is néedfull, and liues for life, not for luſt, longs to bee with God, and delights that natiue Kingdome. It ioyes in the deliuerie from the inticements of the fleſh, world, and diuell, with whom it fights, ſéeking to ſubdue the fleſh by often abſtinence, watching, prayer, and forſaking pompe and pride. But our painting is apparant that we are not in battell, but are inordinate louers of our bodies.</p>
               <p>Good God giue vs grace to amend, that with a liuely faith we may apprehend Chriſts merits, and be cloathed with his white Roabe of righteouſneſſe: to whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt be all honour foreuer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Seruite Iehouae.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19017:21"/>
               <head>
                  <l>Newes to the poore, too good to be true:</l>
                  <l>All will not beleeue it that doth it view.</l>
               </head>
               <l>THe Diuels reioycing doth decreaſe, men ſhew good words &amp; deeds:</l>
               <l>In mutuall comfort, ioy and peace, we croppe vp curſed weedes.</l>
               <l>The Milſayld Ruffs doe all goe downe, and little Bands in place.</l>
               <l>Gods word preuailes in euery Towne; for Pride hath great diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Starch is turned into Bread, yee poore haue oft deſir'd it,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pride-popiniay</hi> doth learne to kneade, which lately did miſlike it.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Light of Loue</hi> is not ſo fine, but frames her ſelfe to thrift;</l>
               <l>And learnes good houſwifery in time, frequenting no euill ſhift.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minion</hi> now muſt make White-meate, full fit ſhe is to learne it:</l>
               <l>To garden, plant, to ſow and ſet, which brings this Realme much profit:</l>
               <l>Cabadge, Mill'ons, Onions, Leekes, betimes in time of yeere:</l>
               <l>Good newes, you poore ſhall haue fat cheekes, foode will not be ſo deare.</l>
               <l>A recompence ſhe now will make for all her time ill ſpent:</l>
               <l>Rememberance doth make her ſhake, and now ſhe doth repent.</l>
               <l>The needle and the ſpindle ſhe full quicke oft time doth vſe,</l>
               <l>And loues in heauenly word to ſee, and doth all vice refuſe.</l>
               <l>She that did watch great Ruffs to ſet, and ſleepe the Sabbath day,</l>
               <l>Attentiue is and vigilant to heare Gods word and pray.</l>
               <l>The Poking-yrons barre the doores, goods ſafe in houſe to keepe,</l>
               <l>From ſuch as doe like knaues and whores, moleſt men in their ſleepe.</l>
               <l>Great holes in cloth cut ſhall not be. Good cloth it will be cheape.</l>
               <l>The poore pray God this thing to ſee, their hearts for ioy doe leape.</l>
               <l>Pinkt Hats on thornes ſhall hang no more, plaine ſtuffe will laſt <hi>3.</hi> yeere;</l>
               <l>You ſhall them haue good Brethren poore ere rugge begin to peere.</l>
               <closer>Valete in Chriſto.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A reproofe of hideous Oathes.</head>
               <p>THE accuſtomable ſinne of Swearing, and deteſtable ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods Name in vaine, apparantly appeare ſuch little or nothing eſtimate his Maieſtie. The manner, <hi>Acrotho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax</hi> and <hi>Acolaſtus</hi> ſweare by him, with dialect diſorder and a brauery in common talke, as it they ſware by <hi>Iohn</hi> or <hi>Ione,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19017:21"/> and ſo vſed in ſporting places, as to heare may mooue a true beleeuing heart to bléede. Not ſo onely, but by all the parts of Chriſt particularly: not conſidering how his parts were pierced for our ſinnes, and we exclude our ſelues from that benefit. The Iewes rent him with nayles, ſtripes, and thornes; and Swaggerers ſtill doe teare him with their tongues.</p>
               <p>Some vſe it in buying, ſelling, and guilefull getting: they are couetous to borrow much, but ſparing to pay. They promiſe, but breake performance, <hi>Aſſertorie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others vſe a perillous petition to get goods: <hi>So GOD iudgeth them:</hi> not conſidering the dreadfull Iudgement and ſeuere ſentence pronounced;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into euerlaſting fire:</hi> when they ſhall obey to their decay.</p>
               <p>Some; <hi>As God ſhall haue part of their ſoule.</hi> Oh wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wretch, thou oweſt not thy ſelfe: GOD will haue thée ſoule &amp; body, or the Diuell ſoule &amp; body. Some by their faith: <hi>Heb. 11. But without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others ſweare by creatures, whereby they diſpleaſe God greatly, which is iealous of his glory; and ſayth, <hi>Ierem. 5.7. How ſhall I pardon thee for this? thy children haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me, and ſworne by them that are no gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To reprooue this and the like, Chriſt ſaith; <hi>Mat. 5.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reproofe of Swearing.</note> 
                  <hi>Let your communication be, Yea, yea: Nay, nay: for whaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is more then this, commeth of euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When wee ſweare we muſt vſe the glorious Name of God with great reuerence and feare:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>(viz.)</hi> Where the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God is ſought, or the ſaluation of our brethren, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Magiſtrate in witneſſing the truth: not in our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, or otherwiſe vainely. It is forbidden, <hi>Leuit. 19.12. And yee ſhall not ſweare by my Name falſely, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhalt thou prophane the Name of thy God, I am the Lord.</hi> Regard it:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>For the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his Name in vaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord hath ſayd, <hi>Zacha. 5.</hi> That the curſe ſhall enter
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19017:22"/> into the houſe of him that ſweares falſely by his Name.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 24.</note>God commaunded, that hee which blaſphemed his Name ſhould bee ſtoned. It was effected, and now is to be wiſhed ſuch ſhould be puniſhed. Although it be reprooued, it is to be feared few will refrayne: for Sathan is ſubtill to ſeduce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts comming, and is induſtrious to draw vs to that God hath forbidden: ſo that ſome, as in their health did ſweare and curſe; ſo haue they in their ſickneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted fearefully. <hi>Eſay 45.9. Woe be to him that ſtriues with his Maker. Conſider this, yee that forget God, leſt I take you away,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.22.</note> 
                  <hi>and there bee none to helpe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh if you knew him, you would quake to blaſpheme him: his glorious brightneſſe excells the Sunne in the Firmament, ſo that ſinfull eyes cannot beholde him. <hi>Eſay 6. Seraphins couer their faces in Gods preſence.</hi> Thou blaſt of breath, bee not ſo ſaucie with the GOD of Might and Maieſtie. <hi>Ieremie 10.6. Foraſmuch as there is none like vnto thee, ô Lord, thou art great, and thy Name is great in might. verſ. 10. At his wrath the earth ſhall tremble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, bragge beggers, bold to diſhonour him, you muſt from wealth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 8.</note> or wealth from you, it is none of yours, honour the owner. The <hi>Pſalmographe</hi> doth ingeminate this; <hi>O Lord our God, how excellent is thy Name in all the earth!</hi> Our Sauiour taught vs to ſay; <hi>Hallowed be thy Name.</hi> Let vs not derogate it. Bad children grieue to ſee their father miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſed: much more Gods children to ſée our heauenly Father abuſed.</p>
               <p>Some leawd of the vulgar heare, and beare with Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Drunkards; but checke ſuch as abhorre it, for any ſmall infirmitie paſt for want of fore-ſight; and with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing make a myte a mountaine. I would I and others had but infirmities; I haue millions of ſinnes, and GOD knowes of more then I can remember. Good God aſſiſt vs to reſiſt and hate ſinne in our ſelues and others, that with ſilence we ſée thee not blaſphemed.</p>
               <p>Common Swearers, are commonly Curſers, and aſkers of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19017:22"/> euill petitions, impious people are wrathfull like the Diuell, aſking plagues, poxe, and all kinde of euill. So ofte times they haue that they craue. Our tongues are not to be vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euils, but to pray to God and praiſe him.</p>
               <p>He that vilifieth his Name, ſhewes himſelfe worſe then a tode, which by ſinging ſets ſorth Gods praiſe. <hi>Pſal. <hi>148.</hi>
                  </hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Dauid</hi> exhorteth créeping things vnrationall, to praiſe GOD, yet men with reaſon blaſpheme him: which none can doe that loue him.</p>
               <p>A preſident repugnant was S. <hi>Dauid, <hi>Bleſſe the Lord, ô my ſoule, and all that is within mee bleſſe his holy Name.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 103.</note> 
                  <hi>Let euery thing that hath breath praiſe the Lord.</hi> And ſhall Man hauing reaſon blaſpheme him?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 150.</note> Oh it is odious to a Chriſtian. Therefore when thou heareſt any take Gods name in vaine, ſay; <hi>Bleſſed be his Name.</hi> If he regard it not, exhort him with leuitie: If he be peruerſe, refraine his companie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> by kéeping <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, learned to ſweare <hi>By the life of Pharaoh:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.</note> but he returned to ſuch vertue as is to be feared few do, for ſin is now ſo auaileable it ſeemeth to be ineuitable</p>
               <p>O arrogant earth, feare the Almighty. Bee not an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell, worſe then the Diuell; <hi>The Diuels belieue, and tremble.</hi> True Faith and true feare hath care to eſchue euill, and doe good. <hi>Prou: <hi>8.13.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iames</hi> 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>The feare of the Lord is to hate euill, pride, and arrogancie, and the euill way, and the froward mouth doe I hate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Blaſpheamer with his froward mouth and black tongue makes his ſoule blacke. GOD made it to praiſe him, not to diſhonour him. He ſaith, <hi>1. <hi>Sam:</hi> 2.30. For them that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour mee, I will honour: and they that deſpiſe mee ſhalbe lightly eſteemed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray to GOD, and praiſe him; none can ſaue thee but hée, and he abhorreth ſinne. <hi>Heb: <hi>1.13. Thou art of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer eyes then to behold euill, &amp; canſt not look on iniquitie.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let vs conſider this, how wee procure Gods anger, and grieue him with our ſinne, by Sathans ſeducing. To ſée him maketh man to quake, but the Swearer ſéemes to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19017:23"/> and feare not. Both muſt be admoniſhed.</p>
               <p>You that with ſilence heare it, and yée that vſe it, leaue it, leaſt in Hell yee languiſh, with blaſpheming and curſing the time of byrth and being. To preuent it, Repent: Loue God and laude him; Elſe at Iudgement day thy conſcience will accuſe thee, Chriſt will refuſe thée, the Hoaſt of Heauen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre thee, and Diuells euer torment thée.</p>
               <p>From which good Lord deliuer vs, for IESVS ſake, that bought vs. To the which GOD Almightie, thrée perſons in Trinitie be all poſſible praiſe for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Benedic anima mea Iehouae.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Inuectiue for Sabbath-Prophaners.</head>
               <p>THe abuſe of the Sabbath doth greatly derogate the glory of God. Vſed of ſome in the Church, of ſome out of the Church. Concerning euill behauiour in the Church, There are certaine ſeduced in greedie getting, or néedleſſe dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; that they goe late, attyred meeter for a Play, then to pray. Whoſe eyes wander in euery corner, and the fineſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion is their proſpect.</p>
               <p>They by watching about their follie, and others (too full fed) doe ſlumber and comber the Church, offending God, and grieuing the good. The hungry ſléepe not at dinner; to ſléepe at a Sermon ſhewes no hungrie deſire: the paunch full is vnfit to pray.</p>
               <p>Sermon-ſléepers, whether <hi>Papiſts</hi> or <hi>Neuters,</hi> intrude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Proteſtants. They eaſe the corps by leaning. So ſhould they the Conſcience, and auoyde ſleeping by ſtanding, but <hi>Pinguitie</hi> preuents it. Ignorants went farre to fall to an Image: Farre and neere, fall thou to the true God. Goe ſooner, and be better prepared to pray, and praiſe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Parents re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke your boyes.</note>Some Ruffians and rude ones, yea, bragge boyes, haue hattes on their heads, when Pſalmes are read or ſung (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayers and petitions.) <hi>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4. Euery man pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or porphecying, hauing his head couered, diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To begge of a King couered, is vncomely; Much more ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19017:23"/> to begge of the King of Kings. Some ſittes, praying the Lords Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthew. <hi>26.39.</hi> CHRIST</hi> did proſtrate and pray becauſe of our ſinnes; and ſhall not we ſinners knéele when we pray? S. <hi>Paule</hi> did it. <hi>Acts <hi>21.5.</hi>
                  </hi> If wee knéele not, ſtanding is fitting, ſo did the poore <hi>Publican: Luke. <hi>18.13.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>GOD ordained body and ſoule, and will be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by both. <hi>1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 6. For yee are bought with a price: Therefore glorifie God in your bodie and in your Spirite, which are Gods.</hi> And if we will not willingly, hée will be glorified in our deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſtand in awe, with inward and outward obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Eſay, <hi>66.5. Heare the word of the Lorde, yee that tremble at his word.</hi> Pſalme <hi>134. Lift vp your hands in the Sanctuarie, and bleſſe the Lorde.</hi>
                  </hi> Bleſſed Preachers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, ſo ought the people.</p>
               <p>Deuout <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal: <hi>63. I will lift vp my hands in thy Name.</hi> Nehemiah. <hi>8.3.</hi>
                  </hi> The people did with willing mindes heare the Word of God, from the morning vntill Midday, and the eares of the people were attentiue. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>5. All the people ſtood vp.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>6. And</hi> Ezra <hi>bleſſed the Lord the great</hi> GOD; <hi>And all the people anſwered,</hi> Amen, Amen; <hi>with lifting vp their hands: and they bowed their heads, and worſhipped the Lorde, with theyr faces to the ground.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such Agilitie moueth vigilancie, as a meanes of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but be frée from hypocriſie, God abhorres it. Be euer more zealous then thou ſéemeſt. Lift vp thy hands, with hart annexed, for hands without heart is abhominable. <hi>verſ. <hi>8. So they read in the booke of the law of God diſtinctly, &amp; gaue the ſence, &amp; cauſed them to vnderſtand the reading.</hi>
                  </hi> Theyr Teachers did comfort them, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>9. For all the people wept.</hi>
                  </hi> Alas, little is our wéeping, much ſléeping. Pride omits ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>Re. <hi>1.7. But all the kinreds of the earth ſhall waile becauſe of him.</hi>
                  </hi> And ſome, ſo ſoone as Sermon is done, wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of worldlineſſe, and are more ſtout then ſtudious. Loue of Riches chokes the Word.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:19017:24"/>
               <p>A good Cow chewes her cud increaſing good bloud, and we muſt meditate in the word whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue heard. If we were pricked in our harts we would ſay to the Preacher, and each to other, as the people to <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts <hi>2.37. Men &amp; Brethren what ſhall we do?</hi>
                  </hi> Then <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid vnto them, <hi>Repent.</hi> We know it, God graunt we may doe it. <hi>Mark: <hi>11.</hi>
                  </hi> Ieſus went into the Temple, and caſt out them that did abuſe the ſame. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er. <hi>16. And would not ſuffer that any ſhould carry any veſſell thorow the Temple.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er. <hi>17. And he taught ſaying vnto them, It is written, My houſe ſhalbe called of all Nations the houſe of Prayer.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Slacke we are to pray, or repaire that Houſe: but where bodyes are fed, and laſts fulfilled, building is not ſpared. For the neglect of building the Lordes Houſe,<note place="margin">Haggai.</note> by them that dwell in their ſteled houſes, the Lord ſtaied Heauen from deaw, and the Earth from her fruite. <hi>Nabuchadnezzer</hi> gloried in his building,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.30.</note> but heard a woefull voyce. Many braue buildings are burned. God make vs more mindefull of his Houſe, and to vſe our ſelues well therein. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of euill behauiour out of the Church.</head>
               <p>THe more a man neglects the means of true knowledge, the liker he is a Beaſt: the more endued with that light of life: the liker hée is his Creatour. Yet Church-ſlée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and ſlack-goers can on the Sabboth haſt to an Alehouſe, and ſay, the Preacher was too tedious, which ſhewes they felt not the ſwéete taſte, for ſuch ſits longer in leaude demeanour and loues it. Men can watch a day to compaſſe a match for backe and belly, or to kéepe ill companie: but to heare glad tidings, is thought tedious. Hee that is wearie of Gods word, is weary of God: Looke into it, It is his Image, by whome the Sonne hath reuealed him.</p>
               <p>As ſome are careleſſe, ſo their Children growe graceleſſe: Boyes are in back-lanes, ſwearing and ſwaggering, in open Stréetes wrangling, in houſes playing, in yardes worrying Dogges and Cattes, committing mercileſſe actions. Had not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19017:24"/> Man ſinned Beaſts had not ſtriued: Some reioyce in the ſight, and in ſinne. Good Parents doe kéepe children and Seruants to their bookes, repeating to them that the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher taught: when lewd ones are in ſtréetes deſturbing them. They that inſtruct not their Familie, are like to féele of theyr follie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> reformed his Houſhold, <hi>Cornelius</hi> feared God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 35. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.</note> with all his houſe. When children diſfigure their faces Parents are grieued: but they ſée them diſfigure their Soules and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it. Let not your Boyes be rude in ſtreetes, to people that paſſe: graceleſſe youth grieue them daily, caſting ſcornefull words or worſe.</p>
               <p>There is difference of Youth; the well trained vp are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, the idle are vicious: and haue cauſe to crie; <hi>Nocet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentia nobis: <hi>Sufferance doth hurt vs.</hi>
                  </hi> Some ſuch, at ten yeares are paſt recouery, hanged by twenty.<note place="margin">Securitants conſider it.</note> Then they crye out of their parents. Had they feared God their children had not miſcaried: For this is his Edict, <hi>Leuitic. <hi>19.30. Yee ſhall keepe my Sabbaths, and reuerence my Sanctuarie;</hi> I am the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuch regarde not, they ſcorne the Aged, that giue them good counſell: yet Age is a Type of Eternitie. And God ſaith, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>32. Thou ſhalt riſe vp before the hoary head, and honour the face of the Olde man, and ſeare thy God;</hi> I am the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that feare God, dare not prophane his Sabbath. But ſome trauell all that day.</p>
               <p>Others heare a Sermon in the Forenoone, and an other in the after: but ſpend the other part of the Day in bargai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and other vnprofitable paſtimes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>GODS WORD</hi> is compared to a Hammer, to breake a ſtone. Oh Sabbath-prophaner art thou harder? Clay, doth the Sunne make thée harde? <hi>Pharaos</hi> heart, art obdurate? Be ſubmiſſe and mollified. Amend, pray, and praiſe God.</p>
               <closer>Laudate nomen Iehouae.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19017:25"/>
               <head>¶ A proofe that the Sabbath muſt be obſerued.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAbbat</hi> ſignifies holy reſt, not ryot. God hath commanded and reſerued that (one whole day of ſeauen) to be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Maieſtie. He gaue the example. <hi>And he reſted on the ſeuenth day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>from all his worke which he had made.</hi> The kéeping of the Sabbath is a Morall precept. God ſpake it, <hi>Exod: <hi>20.</hi>
                  </hi> God wrote it, <hi>Exod: <hi>31.18.</hi>
                  </hi> and the Tables of ſtone being broken, God wrote the ſecond time on tables of ſtone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.</note> as hee did on the firſt. The Sabboth was commanded for a perpetuall couenant, <hi>Ex:<hi>31.16.</hi>
                  </hi> God allowed vs ſixe dayes to worke, &amp; reſerued to himſelfe one, which men would rob him of. The wicked would haue all dayes, and the diuell would haue all ſoules. To worke therein was death, <hi>Ex: <hi>35.</hi>
                  </hi> On which day,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod:</hi> 16.</note> the <hi>Iewes</hi> might kindle no fire. Sixe dayes they might gather <hi>Manna,</hi> on the ſeuenth there was none to be found, they were forbidden to ſéeke it that day, and euery man commanded to abide in his place the ſeueth day.</p>
               <p>God tooke away the occaſion from their labour, ſignifying how holy he would haue the Sabbath kept. It is a Sabbath of reſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23.</note> an holy conuocation, and was commaunded to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated from Euen to Euen. S. <hi>Paule</hi> kept the whole day, and continued his preaching till midnight.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>On the preparation to the Sabbath, the bodie of <hi>IES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> was begged by <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to be buried,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 15. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.</note> for obſeruing the ſabbath. God hath commanded the kéeping thereof, with a <hi>Memento.</hi> Sunday was the firſt day of the Worldes Creation, and the day of Chriſts Reſurrection. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> calles it <hi>Dies Dominicus. <hi>I was in the ſpirit on the Lords day:</hi>
                  </hi> for it was by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles eſtabliſhed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 1.10.</note> and Saturday, the <hi>Iews</hi> Sabbath aboliſhed. Therfore it behooues vs carefully to kéepe Sunday, the Lords day. The Law is perpetuall, ſo is the Sabbath: and is to be ſanctified to Gods ſeruice. For though (being vnder the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) we are deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhadows of the ceremoniall law; yet it foloweth of congruity, that we indeuor to kéepe the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall precepts, and be obedient to Gods commandements; elſe we are not grafied in <hi>Christ,</hi> which ſaith <hi>Math: <hi>5. Thinke not that I am come to deſtroy the law or the prophets, I am not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19017:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> come to deſtroy, but to fulfill.</hi>
                  </hi> If wee belong to him, we will doe our induſtrie. God is iealous of his glory, which men di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, diſhonouring him more on that day, then in all the wéeke. His <hi>Memento</hi> is not minded. Man and beaſt muſt reſt. Yet rude ones ride on the Sabbath vpon ſmall occaſions. All within thy gate muſt reſt (that is) within thy power. Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruants and ſtranger. Sée it performed, preuent eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. By <hi>Chriſt</hi> we haue Chriſtian liberty, to doo things of neceſſity, for preſeruation of life, and of things in vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay on the ſabbath. <hi>Chriſt</hi> then healed a man, and the <hi>Iews</hi> did lift ſhéepe from the pit: and we muſt be carefull that the thing wee doe be ſuch as cannot well be deferred to further time.</p>
               <p>Néedleſſe worldly workes, wordes, and worldly thoughts, muſt be abandoned. <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b: <hi>15.</hi>
                  </hi> God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded all the people to ſtone a man that gathered ſticks on the ſabbath.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math:</hi> 1.80.</note> Oh yee that follow luſts, be obedient, leaſt yee be perpetually puniſhed. God lookes for our Obedience: to obey is better then ſacrifice. <hi>Nehemiah <hi>13.</hi>
                  </hi> reprooued them that brake the ſabbath, in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſheaues, and loading their Aſſes, and that ſolde ware; he told them that euill came on the Cittie, becauſe their Fathers did ſo. The Lord by <hi>Ieremie <hi>17.21.</hi>
                  </hi> dehorteth from breaking the Sabbath, and exhorteth people to hallow the ſame. God promiſeth a bleſſing if they obey: if not, a deſtruction. Ioyfull promiſe is for performance. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord vnto the Eunuches that keep my Sabbaths, &amp; chooſe the things that pleaſe me, and take holde of my Couenant <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. Euen vnto them will I giue in mine houſe; &amp; within my walles a place, and a name better then of ſonnes &amp; of daughters. I wil giue them an euerlaſting name, that ſhall not be cut off.</hi> In this <hi>Maior</hi> is a <hi>Beniſſon,</hi> to him that knoweth not a woman, if hee applie the <hi>Minor.</hi> To euery man that kéepeth the ſabbath (not doing his owne wayes, nor ſpeaking his owne wordes) God hath promiſed a bleſſing. But God is forgotten, and preſent pleaſures thought on. Some ſubſtantiall whome the world eſtéem of, talke on their traſh, ſubtilty, and ſenſualitie on that day: and for a meſſe of potage, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Eſau,</hi> loſe their birthright.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19017:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> Young-men, ſome of them are like a generation of Vipers, ſtarting aſide like a broken Bowe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neuters,</hi> that delight not Gods Lawe, ſay, they belieue as the Church belieueth; and how that is, they knowe not, as though they had a taſte of the Whore of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Lurking Maſſe-mongers doe ſeduce and make them luke-warme.</p>
               <p>The body of <hi>Iezabel</hi> was deuoured, but her Feete, ſkull, and handes remained. And though the light doth diſprooue Idolatrie, ſome with deceiued taſt thereof, would burne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to the Queene of heauen: which God reprooued, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſhed. Conſider it, yée that are thereto addicted. They that loue darknes, ha e the light, leaſt it ſhould reprooue them.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 44.</note> Such are wilfull Abſenters, and ſome that heare, are Sabbath-prophaners. The true vſe of the Sabbath is, with the Aſſembly to heare Gods word read, and preached, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament with thanks and repentance, to pray for our gratious King <hi>Iames,</hi> Quéene, and Royall progenie: and for all Gods children, (being the Church vniuerſall.) O Lord we thanke thee for our dread Soueraigne his great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, from <hi>Iannes, Iambres,</hi> and traitorly <hi>Iudas:</hi> and we beſéech thée to deliuer vs from ſuch mercileſſe papiſts. Amen.</p>
               <p>As at all times, ſo chiefly on the Sabbath, we muſt feede on the word, and thanke our good God; meditate, comfort, and counſell each other, from euill to good; and prouide for the poore at ſuch time of the day, as ſhall not hinder the ſeede ſowne in vs. S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> makes mention of <hi>3.</hi> kind of works, that muſt be done on the Sabbath, <hi>viz:</hi> The works of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, inſtructing the ignorant: the works of Charitie, giuing to the poore. The works of neceſſitie, to ſaue things in vtter decay. As at all times, ſo on this day, let vs comfort the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, &amp; praiſe him, which roſe then for our conſolation and and Iuſtification. The <hi>Iewes</hi> ſabbath did put them in minde of their deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the cruelty of <hi>Pharao</hi> vnto the deſert, where they were fed with <hi>Manna,</hi> and ſo to the promiſed <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi> Our Sabbath puts vs in remembrance of our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the fiery <hi>Pharao</hi> the diuell: and that we ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe eternall reſt, if we obey God, and keepe the true Reſt.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19017:26"/>
               <p>An abſenter ſayes: God heard <hi>Iob</hi> on the dunghil, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the denne; ſo may he me in my houſe. Saint <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal. 122. I was glad when they ſayd vnto mee, Let vs goe into the houſe of the Lord. Pſa. 84. My ſoule longeth, yea euen faynteth for the Courts of the Lord.</hi> Hée accompanied the holy conuocation: <hi>Pſal. 42. I went with them to the houſe of God with the voyce of ioy and prayſe.</hi> It muſt be the finall cauſe. The ſwéete Singer ſaith, <hi>Pſal. 81 Sing aloud vnto God our ſtrength; make a ioyfull noyſe vnto the God of Iacob.</hi> The ruder ſort make not a ioyfull noyſe; they can ſing few tunes for Pſalmes, nor in tune, but diſturbe the Congregation. <hi>Dauids</hi> heart and ſwéete loud voyce makes harmony, illuſtrating the glory of God, which ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heart and voyce. He a type of Chriſt, ſaith; <hi>Pſal. 35.18. I will giue thee thanks in the great congregation, I will prayſe thee among much people.</hi> Louers of God are ioyfull to prayſe him among many, and to ſée God prayſed by many. Let vs not let it, but loue it: imbrace the truth, and prayſe God for it. To the which bleſſed Trinitie be eternall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, prayſe and glory, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Tota ipſa anima laudet Iah.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Againſt the euill effects of Dicing and Carding.</head>
               <p>DIcing and Carding are accuſtomed with company that vſeth exceſſe: they goe to an Alehouſe, and call for an Out-houſe, and ſit wrangling, diſhonouring God, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Sathan, and cauſe vexation. The winner ſpends it prodigally, procuring Gods diſpleaſure. The ſadde lozer gripes for money gréedily; to be reuenged, raſhly hee ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth more, which turnes ſtill to the leſſe. Then the youth entreth into a Shoppe booke; the day come, money hee hath none, his Land is accepted, friendly he is excited: hee makes a ſale, and ſets vp that buyer: the money ſoone ſpent, he ſets vp a wiſpe, and is drudge to ſwearers and drunkards.</p>
               <p>If that ſerues not, then begging, théening, and killing; venturing ſoule and body for money: but tyed at Tiborne,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19017:27"/> take example:<note place="margin">The cry of the careleſſe.</note> Our wofull Parents loued our bodies, but hated our ſoules; woe to the time of that libertie. Yet ſome will not be warned, they are remiſſe in that dutie, and bring their children to miſery. O ſecuritant, thou art the cauſe of thy childes deſtruction, if not damnation; and thy childe the meanes of thine. Hadſt thou béene carefull, his precious time had not béene ſpent in play: whereof came idle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſtrife, ſwearing, pouerty, théeuing, hanging, (preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall effects of dicing and carding.) Some ſay, My ſonne is no Dicer nor Carder: but thou permitſt him to a proparatiue by ſuch like play. All euill is ſo prompt to ſpring from our corrupt natures, that euill learned in youth is hard to bee remooued: if good, it is like to bee ſetled. Therefore rightly are children compared to Veſſels which commonly kéepe the taſte of the firſt liquor. Yet many will not be counſelled, but giue euill example to their houſehold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tully</hi> toucheth them: <hi>Plus nocent exemplo quam peccato: <hi>They hurt more by the example then by the thing it ſelfe.</hi>
                  </hi> The actions of Houſe-kéepers doe animate the houſehold. <hi>Eph. 5.16.</hi> Men muſt redéeme the time. Vertue muſt bee annexed to faith. Let vs vſe holy conuerſation and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Paſſe the time of your ſoiourning heere in feare.</hi> To preuent youths vicinitie to vice: in ſtead of dice and card<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reade good bookes, pray, and prayſe God. Euery minute requires the aduancement of Gods glory, and good of each other.</p>
               <p>Vnprofitable actions become not Chriſtians, they are no motiues to mooue men to praiſe GOD. Careleſſe Libertines muſt leaue them: they are no good works of the Goſpell, nor the light Chriſt gaue charge ſhould ſhine among men: but meanes to haue God blaſphemed, and the Diuell ſerued. They are no holy actions, no fruits of the Spirit; rather wantonneſſe, whereof enſueth contentions and fruits of the fleſh. A good trée brings foorth good fruit, <hi>Mathew 7.</hi> The fruitleſſe combers the ground,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.19</note> like the wilde Figge trée that Chriſt withered.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as the effects of carding and dicing are euill,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19017:27"/> and the exerciſe thereof may bee left without damage to any, it is ſufficient to prooue they ought not to bee vſed. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue many things in briefe:<note place="margin">1. <hi>The.</hi> 5.22</note> 
                  <hi>Abſtaine from all appearance of euill;</hi> (that is) from things that haue a ſhew of euill, much more from things meanes of euill.</p>
               <p>The effects ſhew that dicing and carding cauſeth euill: Not to mée, nor by mée, ſaith one. Oh, thou ſpendeſt the time that might be ſpent better, and ſheweſt an euill example farre from grauitie and integritie. Whatſoeuer are appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of euill ought to bee omitted: but dicing and carding are appearance of euill; <hi>ergo,</hi> they ought to bee omitted. The aſſumption is prooued by the euill effects; beſides, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence giuen to the godly. <hi>Mathew 18.</hi> Chriſt pronounceth woe to Offenders. <hi>1. Cor. 8 13.</hi> Some néedfull things are to be omitted to auoyd offence; much more, néedleſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer is vnprofitable, and may bee omitted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out damage, ought not to bee vſed: but carding and dicing are vprofitable and may bee omitted without da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: <hi>ergo,</hi> they ought not to be vſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dicing and carding, which conſiſteth méerely vpon blinde hazard, lot and chance are to be reiected. Dicing conſiſts in lot-caſting, being a religious ordinance for ſerious matters to determine doubtfulneſſe. Lotte was caſt for <hi>Mathias, Acts 1. God is the diſpoſer of the Lot.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.33.</note> Oh it is baſe to bée vſed in boyes play.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Publius; <hi>Quanto alcator in arte melior est, tanto nequior eſt:</hi> How much the Dicer is cunning in his Arte, ſo much the worſe hee is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Amb. lib. 1. De offic. chap. 23.</hi> Playes &amp; paſtimes are ſwéete when they are repugnant to the rules of chriſtianitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ciprian;</hi> Play at Cards is an inuention of Satan, which he found out that he might the eaſier bring in Idolatry: for the coat cards which are vſed, were ſometime the Images of Idols and falſe gods. <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperour abhorred Dice play, &amp; by his <hi>Authenicall</hi> Lawes ſuppreſſed it. <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> forbid it; <hi>Preachers</hi> reprooue it; for the word of God doeth menace it; the <hi>Fathers</hi> reiect it; and the <hi>Pagans</hi> deteſt it.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19017:28"/> 
                  <hi>Gen. 1.27.</hi> Man was inueſted in Gods likeneſſe: we ſhould imitate Gods properties: hee wrought that could make all things at a thought:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15.</note> and ſo appoynted vs. <hi>And the Lord God tooke the man, and put him into the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> to dreſſe it and to keepe it.</hi> If man in his inocencie ought to worke, much more now being polluted. <hi>Gen. 3.19. In the ſweate of thy face ſhalt thou eate bread, till thou returne vnto the ground.</hi> Some will not worke in Winter, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore begge in Summer. It is written, <hi>2. Theſſ. 3. That if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would not worke, neyther ſhould they eate.</hi> If thou be wealthy, and wilt not worke: <hi>Adam</hi> was wealthier, and hée wrought. Walke thou in the Fields, behold Gods bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and prayſe him. Walke in thy houſe, pray, read, and meditate: for dicing and carding is vnwholſome, &amp; bréedes Gout and Dropſie. They bee called honeſt recreations; yet Sathans inuentions. The prophane are cald Good fellowes; ſo haue béene Diuels. Gods word doth direct vs to paſſe the ſhort time of our pilgrimage: <hi>Iames 5.13. Is any among you afflicted? let him pray. Is any merry? let him ſing Pſalmes.</hi> But prayer ſeemes vnpleaſant, and Pſalmes too much ſolemnity. Hymnes and ſpirituall ſongs ſome haue no ſkill in, when bawdy catches delight them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.</note>Idle words, for which men ſhall giue an account of at the day of Iudgement, ſéeme ſwéete. Idle words are, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anae &amp; inutiles nugae in quibus plerique vitam terunt: <hi>Vaine and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable tryfles, in which many waſte their life.</hi>
                  </hi> Idleneſſe is the cauſe of idle words. <hi>Otium puluinar est Satanae: <hi>Idleneſſe is a Feather-bed of the Diuell.</hi>
                  </hi> Idle words are with idle actions. You turne the Dye, thinke how you turne to folly. Thou doeſt caſt thy Card, thinke how you caſt away time. Thou bidſt thy Bowl rub, thinke thou ſhalt be rotten. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne from vanitie, and alſo crueltie: ſée no blinde things fight, nor blinde Beares whipt. <hi>Mat. 5. Bleſſed are the mercifull.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>A righteous man regardeth the life of his beaſt.</hi> Let good motiues bee a meanes to preuent ſuch paſtimes as are meanes to preuent repentance. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Watch and pray.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41.</note> The world ſaith, <hi>Watch and play.</hi> The holy Ghoſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19017:28"/> bids vs, <hi>Heb. 12. Follow peace with all men, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> But common Gameſters are commonly wranglers, and ſéeme voyd of peace and holineſſe. O yée that haue play vſed in your hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, loſe not Paradiſe for pelfe. It was decréed in the time of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> that ſuch houſes ſhould be confiſcat. In ſtead of Cardes and Tables, haue a Bible on thy Table. Put off and abhorre euill. <hi>Eph. 4.24. And that yee put on that new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt nor his Apoſtles were no gameſters: yet the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine that ſhould learne to read, makes gaming his <hi>ſummam voluptatem,</hi> and ſaith it refreſheth his wit: but that which is ſwéeteſt refreſheth the wit ſooneſt. The Prophet ſaith;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119. <hi>verſ.</hi> 103.</note> 
                  <hi>How ſweet are thy words vnto my taſte: yea ſweeter then honey to my mouth. <hi>verſ.</hi> 62. At midnight I will riſe to giue thanks vnto thee, becauſe of thy righteous iudgements.</hi> That time is pleaſant to play; but not for them to giue thanks and pray. Then they throw pots at each other, with ſuch ſwearing and blaſpheming of God, as is grieuous. <hi>Verſ. 148. Mine eyes preuent the night watches, that I might meditate in thy word:</hi> but others refuſe their reſt, to ryot. He deſired Gods word farre aboue fine gold,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.</note> and thought it ſwéeter then the hony combe. Others refuſe it, for dice, cards, &amp; wanton com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. The ſanctified, grieuing for their ſinnes, ſéeke in Gods word for ſwéete comfort: but ſuch as loue leawdneſſe get falſe comfort by laſciuiouſnes. They refuſe Gods word: play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wantonneſſe, and fooliſh ieſting, is a ſalue for their ſore. Bleſſed is he that can ſay in his heart: <hi>Pſa. 119.97. O, I loue thy Lawe, it is my meditation all the day.</hi> Pray for that minde, yee that prophane euery day.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.</note> Gods precepts muſt bée as frontlets betwéene mens eyes: they are Gods childrens paſtime. The impious vſe an <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> and paſſe their time with contraries; they ſay they are the apter; but it is to euill. So the Diuell ſeduced <hi>Eue</hi> to thinke, that by eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit their eyes ſhould be opened, and be as Gods:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> but it was to the ruine of them and theirs. <hi>Re. 4.</hi> In heauen
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19017:29"/> God is prayſed continually; and canſt not thou endure it at voyd times? O rich earth, poore earth, proud earth, loue God, and vſe it on earth. Be not graceleſſe and ſhameleſſe to omit vertuous ſinging, reading, conference, prayer, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to vſe dice and carding. Doe not procraſtinate, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſpéedily, and ſpend thy ſhort time profitably. Be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit for the day of the Lord: <hi>Luk. 21.35. For as a ſnare ſhall it come on all them that dwell on the face of the whole earth. Verſ. 36. Watch ye therfore, and pray alwaies, that ye may bee accounted worthy to eſcape all theſe thinges that ſhall come to paſſe, and to ſtand before the Sonne of man. 2. Pet. 1. And giue diligence to make your calling &amp; election ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O conſider, we can ſpare no time for idle playing, nor idle ſpeaking.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</note> The earth which bringeth thornes and bryers is reiected. <hi>1. Pet. 1.13. Wherefore gird vp the loynes of your minde, be ſober, and hope to the ende.</hi> Let vs doe well, leſt God come with deuouring fire and finde vs euill occupied. Let the remembrance of his ſudden comming preuent euill in thée; againe &amp; againe, I beſéech thee. <hi>Soli Deo laus &amp; gloria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A meanes of amendment.</head>
               <p>FOraſmuch as many liue liker Atheiſts then true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, here are certaine motiues to excite to amend. Many ſeruing Sathan, can boaſt they ſhall bee ſaued, not come to the ſteppe of pietie, to hate iniquitie, that they may apply Chriſts righteouſnes to their conſcience. That moſt of this world ſhall be ſaued, many places of holy writ refelleth. <hi>Mat. 22.14. <hi>Multi ſunt vocati, pauci vero clecti:</hi> Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> It followes, few ſhall be ſaued: O feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſequell! O conſider thine eſtate, hee without whom is no ſaluation ſpake it. <hi>Heb. 9.28. Chriſt was once offered to beare the ſinnes of many:</hi> yet few ſaued relatiuely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the damned. His death is ſufficient; but few haue that ſeruent faith, whoſe effect is a godly life. Chriſt giueth a cauent:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Enter ye in at the ſtraight gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to deſtruction: and many there bee which goe in thereat. 14. Becauſe ſtraight is the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19017:29"/> gate, and narrow is the way which leadeth vnto life, and few there be that finde it.</hi> Conſider the oppoſitions: The broad way to deſtruction many walke: the narrow way to life few finde. The entrance is ſtraight, the paſſage troublous, ſharpe, and full of difficulties, vnpleaſant and repugnant to the pleaſurable broad way. Gods word is the right rule from which men make an aberration. And Chriſt is the true way; but he that is in Chriſt is a new creature. And to ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſo to be, ſo many temptations, rebukes, and tryals, wait on that vertuous life as few endure. Troubles with pietie is a Chriſtians liuery: here is little or no Alcion time. <hi>We muſt through much tribulation enter into the kingdome of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22.</note> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Luke 13.14. Striue to enter in at the ſtraite gate: for many, I ſay vnto you, will ſeeke to enter, and ſhall not be able.</hi> This command and the reaſon might excite vs to cut off all obſtacles, and haue godly ſtrife, rife to excell in vertue. Alas, our ſtriuing and ſeeking is in the broad way, hauing a forme of pietie, denying the power thereof: few leaues, fewer fruit. The fiue fooliſh ſought and craued,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</note> but were excluded: the faith that brings foorth good fruits is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. <hi>Belialls may Iaunce</hi> themſelues. Iuſticiaries whippe themſelues, without true touch of conſcience, as appeares by their preſent committing of incontinencie, and bloudy maſſacry. The prophane may follow iniquitie, preſume on Gods mercy, and ſinne in ſuch ſéeking: the beſt is neglected, the worſt is delighted. Many are perfidious, elſe they would beleeue Chriſts words, and be zealous to amend. Conſider ſeuere ſayings, <hi>Mathew 20.16. 2. Eſd. 8. The moſt High hath made this world for many; but the world to come for few.</hi> Saint <hi>Aug.</hi> affirmes it; <hi>Si omnes liberarentur, foret, vt abſconditum eſſet quod peccato debetur propter iuſtitiam; Sin autem nemo liberaretur, foret, vt non appareret quod per gratiam donatur.</hi> If all ſhould bee deliuered, that were hid which by Iuſtice is due for ſinne: but if no man ſhould bée deliuered, that ſhould not appeare which is giuen through grace. Wée are all by nature the children of wrath: it is Gods mercy to ſaue any.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19017:30"/>
               <p>The Elect ſhallbe ſaued: they with a liuely faith are louers and liuers of righteouſnes: to that end ſuch are deliuered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fewer then the faithles.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.17.</note> Chriſts death is ſufficient for all, but not effectuall to all; the fault is in vs ſinfull people.</p>
               <p>Oh let vs pray and repent, with auerſion from ſinne, and conuerſion to godlineſſe: for right beleeuing hath good liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without which liuely faith we pertaine not to Chriſt; for that liuely faith apprehendeth him, which makes vs iuſt, in that reſpect wee are iuſtified: not formally, as it is inherent righteouſnes in vs; but relatiuely, in reſpect of the obiect: for we are vnrighteous;<note place="margin">Be a good Souldier.</note> therefore we muſt reſiſt ſin continually, which is ſo ſharpe a life as few vſe. <hi>Luke 8.</hi> Séede was ſowen in <hi>4.</hi> places, but one fertill. Impious people are plenty; ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied are dainty. <hi>Ariſt. <hi>Plurima peſſima:</hi> The moſt men are the worſt. <hi>Precioſa non ſunt numeroſa:</hi> Good men are leaſt in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> When all the world was drowned in the deluge, but <hi>8.</hi> faithfull were preſerued: before, many heard of it, but few would be warned.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> When the Lord rayned vpon <hi>Sodom</hi> and vpon <hi>Gomorrah</hi> brimſtone and fire from heauen, thrée were ſegregated from thouſands. <hi>Exo. 12.37. And the children of Iſrael iournied from Ramaſes to Succoth about 600000. on foot that were men, beſide children.</hi> God ſaid; <hi>Surely, there ſhall not one of this euill generation ſee that good Land which I ſware to giue vnto your Fathers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Caleb, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua,</hi> and little ones were accepted; the other were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to turne backe. How many were excluded from the heauenly Canaan, which this Land was a type of, I leaue to the Lord. It is a fearefull example, <hi>Pſa. 95.11:</hi> for he calles it his Reſt. It is mentioned, <hi>Eze. 14.22.</hi> Among many God reſerued but a ſmall remnant for his Church.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.27.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> doeth paralell the place of <hi>Eſay 10.22. Eſaias alſo cryeth concerning Iſrael; though the number of the children of Iſrael bee as the ſand of the Sea, a remnant ſhall be ſaued.</hi> Theſe documents, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther threatnings, ſhould deterre men from their owne detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, but caſt them downe to hell. And ſpared not the old World. And turning the Cities of Sodome and Gomorrah into aſhes, condemned
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19017:30"/> them with an ouerthrow, making them an enſample vnto thoſe that after ſhould liue vngodly.</hi> Yet conſcience is ſcant, ſinne is exceſſiue. <hi>Mat. 24.37. As the daies of <hi>Noah</hi> were, ſo ſhall alſo the comming of the Sonne of man be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider the compariſon. They eat and dranke, ſo do wée ſuperfluouſly: they bought and ſould, ſo doe we deceitfully: they loued the world, ſo doe we egregiouſly: here repugnant; they planted, we plucke vp, to the preiudice of the next poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. Euery one for himſelfe; the Prouerbe is fearfull. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie are deluded, and from Heauen excluded; For God is not feared. Chriſt bids vs watch for his ſudden comming. Theſe motiues might mooue vs to contrition, vigilant expectation, and ſupplicate for mercie euery houre.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Sodom</hi> and her ſiſter were conſumed, and all the world drowned, few faithful were found. How few God ſhall find, when hée comes with fierce Fire, hée <hi>Omniſcient</hi> knowes. He ſhewes by his Word, the world ſhall be worſe. <hi>Luke <hi>18.8. When the Son of man cometh, ſhall he find Faith on earth?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas, what order of life will this world leade? No true Faith, no Saluation. This excites to examine our ſelues, not doing as moſt do. For Atheiſme, Neuteriſme, Self-loue, Idolatry, and all other impietie cryes in the eares of the Lord that liuely Faith is little, and that Chriſt ſhall finde very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. The Diuells leaſe drawes to ende, therefore he is gréedy to get. <hi>Reu. <hi>12. Woe to the inhabitants of the earth, and of the Sea, for the Diuell is come downe vnto you, hauing great wrath, becauſe hee knoweth he hath but a ſhort time.</hi> Mark. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </hi> When Chriſt commanded him out of a Childe, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>26. He cryed, and rent him ſore, and came out of him.</hi>
                  </hi> So now his time is ſhort, and hée makes hauocke, fiercely ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whom he may deuoure.</p>
               <p>Hee aymes at the vertuous: ſo doe his Adherents. He ſpares ſuch as ſerue him, he knowes they are his; they helpe him to entice Gods children. <hi>Hillarius. Dulce Diabolo, nos poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care. <hi>It is ſweete to the Diuell to ſee vs ſinne.</hi> Leo: aut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrat mortes, aut impetit mores. <hi>If he cannot kill a man, he will corrupt him.</hi>
                  </hi> He is ſubtill to ſeduce. This worlde growes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19017:31"/> vngodly, the néerer the ende, the more vngodly.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> prophecied, <hi>2. <hi>Tim:</hi> 3. This know alſo, that in the laſt dayes, perillous times ſhall come.</hi> Hee expreſſeth a Catalogue, whereby is apparant, that men ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of capitall ſinnes. <hi>Traytours, heady, high-minded, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of pleaſures more then louers of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It appeares people will grow graceleſſe, God little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but diſhonoured, and luſts fulfilled: ſo that ſuch as run to riot, ſhall liue moſt in quiet, and that any thing that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth ſinne, wil be much gaine got by, the Diuell and all quickly. Bawdy Bookes will be peruſed, the good leſſe vſed. A floud of wickednes will flowe. The prophane ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled: Good people not eſtéemed. For haters of that which moſt ſhall loue, ſhalbe hated: and moſt men ſhall make plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures their God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That which men ſhall loue moſt they ſhall make their God.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>But men ſhall loue pleaſures moſt. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Men ſhall make pleaſures their God.</l>
               </q>
               <p>It may be ſaide then of Selfe-loue, Pride, and Pleaſure, <hi>Haec tria pro Trino Numine mundus habet. <hi>This is the Trinitie which the world doth worſhip.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> forewarned the olde World; which was drowned. Preachers do teach vs, Lawes doth enforce vs, yet our harts are vnreformed. The righteous ſoule of <hi>Lot</hi> was vexed at peoples impietie, which were deſtroyed, and hee preſerued. <hi>2. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.9. The Lorde knoweth how to deliuer the godly out of temptations, and to reſerue the vniuſt vnto the day of iudgement to be puniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Gods ſeuere threatnings, nor louing admonitions, the multitude deſtroyed, the ſmall number preſerued, make vs not to amende: Yet thinke of Chriſts wordes, whereby is ſhewed few are ſaued in reſpect of the damned. A malefactor feareth no halter till he haue it; and many feare no Hell, till they féele it; Therfore to ſuch I expreſſe an <hi>Epitome</hi> of paines.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A ſhort diſcourſe of long Destruction.</head>
               <p>THe Pangs of Hell are ſo vnſpeakeable, as no mortall tongue can expreſſe. The Damned ſhall féele the ſeuere
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19017:31"/> wrath of God lie vpon them for euer; which is greater &amp; ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then all Fier, Swords, Paines, &amp; Plagues of this world. They ſhall be enuironed, filled, terrified, and tormented of dreadfull Diuels whom they haue ſerued. Soule and bodie for euer ſhall ſuffer horror. A liuing death, pangs muſt be abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. A dying life neuer ended. An euerlaſting burning intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, yet in explicable: Our fire may be extinguiſhed, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is fier that neuer ſhalbe quenched, the deſtruction is euerlaſting.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>2. <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 1.9.</hi> Infinite pangs are prepared for the enemies of the infinite GOD. Had they euer liued here, they had euer bene obſtinate, therefore euer puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Feare and tremble, yee that derogate God of his glory, and attribute it to creatures. Yée prophane Prodigalls, bolde to blaſpheme him, burne not in Brimſtone.</p>
               <p>Oh Atheiſt, belieue in the Almightie; O Neuter, nouriſh no iniquitie. Brutiſh Bawds, ſucking Sodomites, Corne-hoorders, ſore-ſtallers, poore-ſtaruers, pitileſſe partialls, which concurre to defraude the friendles, in hell is direfull <hi>eiulation.</hi> Our fire is ordained to comfort, that to torment: ours giueth light, that vtter darknes. Our fire is ſubſtantiall, ſo is that. But our fire waſteth that it burneth: but hell fire much hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, burneth ſoules and bodies, yet waſteth them not. <hi>Math: <hi>5.22.</hi> Christ</hi> threatneth with hell-fire. There wilbe <hi>Paſſion, Propaſſion, Sympathie,</hi> &amp; fellow-ſéeling of ſoule &amp; bodie: And for finite lewd pleaſures togither, they ſhall haue infinit pangs. <hi>Pſ: <hi>11.6. Vpon the wicked he ſhall raine ſnares, fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, &amp; an horrible tempeſt, this ſhalbe the portion of their cup.</hi>
                  </hi> The ſulphureous pit is déepe and dolefull. <hi>Pſalm. <hi>9.17. The wicked ſhalbe turned into hell, and all the Nations that forget God.</hi> Math: <hi>22. They ſhalbe bound hand &amp; foot, and caſt into vtter darknes, there ſhalbe weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi>
                  </hi> Couſeners, Théeues, and Murderers, which flée with mens goods, ſhall there be ſtayed.</p>
               <p>Thou ſtarter return, leaſt death &amp; hell follow thée. As the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Impious aſcended not to Heauen, but were holden downe to the luſts of their bodies: So ſoule and bodie ſhall deſcend downe to Hell torments, and therein be holden.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19017:32"/> 
                  <hi>Ezek: <hi>32.</hi>
                  </hi> The prophet ſpeaketh of the wicked, that they are gone down to hell. <hi>Pſ. <hi>55. Let them go downe quick to hell.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the ſmoke of theyr Torment aſcenth vp for euer and euer: And they haue no reſt day nor night.</hi> Hell is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, fearfull, and farre from Gods fauour.</p>
               <p>There is no hope of health, no remedy for reliefe, they ſigh and ſorrow in death euer, but die neuer. Here children ſée pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, &amp; parents theyr children run to hell, and may helpe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In inferno nulla redemptio: quoniam nec pater ibi poteſt adiuuare filium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug:</note> 
                  <hi>nec filius patrem. <hi>In Hell is no redemption, for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot helpe the ſonne, nor the ſonne his Father.</hi> Luke. <hi>16.24.</hi> Diues</hi> could not haue one drop of water to coole his tongue, tormented in this flame.</p>
               <p>If Securitants did but touch our fire, and thinke of Hell fire, they would conſider. To ſee the Diuell here in his vglie ſhape, would diſtract the ſtouteſt; and to heare ſoules ſkréeke, affright them; to looke downe ſo déepe, diſmay them.</p>
               <p>Oh vnſpeakeable to ſée and féele the Diuell drawe them downe, and torment them. O yée which conſult to deceiue the friendles: and if yée obtaine it not, it's him you ayme at: vſe not oppreſſion, make reſtitution. Haſte not to Hell, there Pangs pricketh, Feare frighteth, Fire frieth, Diuels diſmay men, and griefe of Conſcience gripes them. To be terrified in hell torments one minute, is more bitter then a thouſand yeares pleaſure here is ſwéete.</p>
               <p>Yée <hi>Sarcaſticall</hi> ſcorners, that reioyce in Sodiſme, conſider this. And ye that blaſpheme Gods Name, Preſuppoſe (I pray) that one in hell were here againe, vpon condition to be a true Chriſtian;<note place="margin">A ſuppoſall.</note> Oh he would faſt, pray, crie for mercy, and mourne for peoples miſerie: not ceaſſing, but ſaying, People repent, turne vice to vertue; It may be, his conſorts erſt in ſenſualitie, would mourne and admire it, which now heare of hell, and amend not.</p>
               <p>Pray and repent, for none can come from hell to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, but are holden in chaines, euer in pangs, eaſeleſſe, hopeleſſe, and remedileſſe. Embracers of Whores ſhall be bruiſed of Diuels. Myrth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Meretrix,</hi> wil cauſe ſad conflicts.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19017:32"/>
               <p>Leaud eyes ſhall ſée <hi>Lucifer.</hi> For light regard of Gods <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,</hi> they ſhall haue miſerie. For detaining goods wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, foule Fiendes ſhall wring thée. He that borroweth like a lamb, and detaineth like a Lyon, ſpeaking euill in ſtéede of payment, ſhalbe pained. Lyons haue pittie. Maſties miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate their furie. But the Diuell is euer furious. His adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents here are mercileſſe, to make the aged ioyleſſe.</p>
               <p>They ſpight at theyr proſperitie, reioyce at their aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: they doe them wrong, make them ſad, and account them Melancholy. The ſtout are aſtonied, when God ſends thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning: much more ſhall they feare, when fierce Fire ſhall pierce them, and Sathan torment them in the loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Lake of lamentation.</p>
               <p>The fearfull flaſhing Fier, the ſpight of dreadfull Diuells, the ſobbing ſighes of ſoules, the roaring of fierce Fiendes, filthie ſauours, and dolefull deane, though they felt no other paine, will be able to breake the heart; if ſo, paines would not decreaſe.</p>
               <p>Curſes then ſhall be effected. <hi>Deuteron: <hi>27.19. On him that peruerteth the iudgement of the Stranger, Fatherleſſe,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zach:</hi> 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and Widow;</hi> the féeling of the full reuealing of the wrath of God will be woefull.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> ſpeaking of the puniſhment of men for vices, ſaid in this <hi>6.</hi> book of <hi>Aeneydes, <hi>A hundred tongues ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not expreſſe the paines men ſuffer in Hell.</hi>
                  </hi> For lothſome Luſt, they haue loſt the vnſpeakable Ioyes of Heauen, and procured the <hi>Pinching pangs</hi> of hell; baniſhed from God and his Saints for euer, to be with vgglie Diuells, <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Iulians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be excluded from Heauen, and included in a Priſon, without paine were yrkeſome: But to be in that Pit in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable pangs and endleſſe, is moſt grieuous.</p>
               <p>They ſhall be euer ſhut out from the dore of Gods mercie: <hi>CHRIST</hi> will ſay, <hi>Depart from me, yee curſed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math:</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fier, prepared for the Diuell, and his Angells.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſts comming to ſuch will be terror, his ſeuere Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence more terror, Hell torments moſt terrible. Chriſt will diuide his Shéepe from the Goates. <hi>Math: <hi>3. And gather his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19017:33"/> Wheate into the Garner, but will burne vp the Chaffe with vnquenchable Fire.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the workers of iniquitie ſhalbe where is wéeping and gnaſhing of téeth, when they ſhall ſée <hi>Abraham, Iſaack,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 13.</note> and all the Prophets in the Kingdome of God.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Diues</hi> ſaw <hi>Lazarus</hi> with <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo ſhall the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſée Gods Children. And thereat bee vexed and amazed, ſighing and ſaying they had ſuch in deriſion. <hi>Scurrilous Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſmus</hi> ſhall confeſſe his fooliſhnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mockers ſhall mourne.</note>Couzeners which ſcorne true dealers ſhall lament with Heart-ſmart, and heauy Hey-hee. <hi>1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.18.</hi> Had they bene Fooles of this world, and belong'd to <hi>CHRIST,</hi> they had bene dignified, not damned.</p>
               <p>The craftie crue ſhall haue ſcalding. For leaudneſſe, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing. For abuſing of Wealth, wayling. For Adultery, Deſtruction; vttering and iterating, Woe worth the time they hated to be counſelled.</p>
               <p>If a malefactor were caſt into a burning Brickkill, he would ſtare and ſtart, ſtamp hee could not, but be quicke diſpatched. Why then are wée ſo farre from ſeruing God, and néere Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than in ſinning, to procure endleſſe Hell fire?</p>
               <p>Men heare this, and liue amiſſe, becauſe they are grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe: the Neuer-dying worme, and dreadfull ſecond death is procured. We imbrace preſent pleaſure, and feare no fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture paine.</p>
               <p>Some liue as though there were no Hell, and aſke where it is, haſting thither. O our euill Affections are below, and Hell is lower. <hi>Prou: <hi>15.24.</hi>
                  </hi> It is beneath, vnpleaſant, Painfull. Hell is déepe. <hi>Prou: <hi>9.18.</hi>
                  </hi> The Damned are voyde of hope and recouerie. The vnſatiable ſhall féele, that <hi>(Prou: <hi>27.) Hell and deſtruction are neuer full.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is large and déepe for manie, yea for moſt. The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Rich, and wicked Poore, ſhall into the gulfe of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyles.</p>
               <p>In the two laſt Chapters of the <hi>Reuel:</hi> is mentioned a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of manie that ſhall into Hell, they ſhall finde and féele it ſo <hi>Circumſcriptiua,</hi> that they ſhall neuer bee in Heauen,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19017:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> which GOD hath prepared for his Elected; and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Hell for the Reiected: they are <hi>Oppoſites:</hi> For in this there is partition of Affection, and the contrarietie of effects euer ſhalbe.</p>
               <p>In Heauen Ioy, and praiſing of GOD amongſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: In Hell horror, curſing theyr Parents, Byrth, and béeing amongſt Diuels. Hideous ſights will affright them, and eternall Fire afflict them.</p>
               <p>Thou Loyteror, that canſt not abide to labour; how wilt thou then abide then to languiſh? Sathan enticeth thée to tuſh, but tuſh wilbe turned to terror; for déedes of darknes, thou ſhalt haue fire and darknes.</p>
               <p>Deuils will daunt thée, they roare irefully, Soules ſkréeke mournfully: the intollerable torments are abideleſſe, and endleſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Minos examen, Radamanthus dat cruciamen: tertius heu Frater, tertia iura tenet.</hi> One Diuell rippeth vp thy exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: an other Diuell tormenteth thée; and the third is not behinde to adde one torment to an other.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt bee prickt for thy Impietie, pierced for thy Periurie: thy hatred to ſuch as abhorred thy leaude life ſhal hurt thée. Thou ſhalt féele how the Diuell deceyued thée here, to torment thée there.</p>
               <p>The partiall, that doe euill one for another, ſhalbe in Hell together. Here is <hi>Time,</hi> men muſt redéeme it; after this Life, no time but Eternitie. Once in Hell and euer, without mitigation, or intermiſſion.</p>
               <p>Oh how ſhall the ſoule and body abide ſuch torments, as are ſharper then all the diſeaſes of this world are, being vpon one lying aliue here in a fiery Furnace? A minute of time would kill vs.</p>
               <p>When millions of millions of yeares are expired, th'ende there is not the néerer. It is no Leaſe, but endleſſe.</p>
               <p>Conſider this. yée that ſéeke out the helpleſſe, and borrowe their goods by great proteſtations, yet detaining, not fearing Conuiction; as if for a diſh of Apples, yee could preuent the right of the Friendleſſe: <hi>Iudas</hi> reſtored, you ſtore it.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19017:34"/>
               <p>A little Thiefe goes mourning to the gallowes, when a greater reioyceth in guilefull getting. Shifters that aſſiſt him, are not much vnlike him.</p>
               <p>In Hell ſuch wrongers ſhall bee wrung. There will be Roaring, Skriking, Garboyles, Griefe, Gingling, Glaring, Staring, Crying, Mourning, Howling, Sighing, Sob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, Stretching, Panting, Gaſping, Gnaſhing, wringing Mouthes, Handes and Bodyes: thinke on Death, thinke on this, it's fearfull to heare, worſe to féele. Many are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to eſcape it, but loue of Luſt lets it. Tooth-ake is paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and Heart-ake giues the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ale;</hi> but in Hell, all parts are euer perplexed.</p>
               <p>Sathan hath couſened ſome to ſhorten their dayes, that could not endure griefe: which they would neuer haue done, had they knowne the pangs of Hell: they that regarde not GOD here, ſhall feare, and féele his Iudgements there.</p>
               <p>Oh hard heart, that no call can penetrate, thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, too late ſhall be thy contrition. For in Hell is woe and wayling, horror, and terror. <hi>Reuela: <hi>20.</hi>
                  </hi> It is a bottome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pitte, for the pittileſſe, a Lake of fier and Brimſtone. <hi>Where the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet are, and ſhall be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented day and night, for euer and euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Quarrellers ſhall quell in hell, Murtherers ſhall mourne, the bloud-thirſtie, ſhall be thirſty. Thieues booties ſhall be bitter. Pangs endleſſe, will make them comfortleſſe. The worme of Conſcience remaineth, fierce Fier endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</p>
               <p>O Idolator pray to God, to no creature. Saints ſearch not thy heart, but onely thy Creator: the Curſed ſhall be cruſhed in the burning Lake, which is the Second-death.</p>
               <p>When ſo many yeares are expired, as in Earth and Sea are ſands, and droppes of water, the ende is not the néerer. Leaue leaudnes, belieue this; It's better to be a toade, then to féele this. Seruers of ſinne, ſhalbe ſubiect to Sathan. Hautineſſe cauſeth heauineſſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 50.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Now conſider this; yee that forget <hi>GOD.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19017:34"/> Art thou couetous and voluptuous, flattering Superiours, defrauding Inferiours? let not pleaſure, mucke and mony hale thée to hel, giue that which hurts thée to them that haue not. Art thou wealthy &amp; wilfull? it is wofull: with a naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie matter do not perſeuere, and vndoe men for euer. Adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be no aſſiſters, repugne euill doers. Burne not; for, <hi>bona omiſſa, mala co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſa:</hi> the pangs are ſo intollerable, as to thinke on is terrible. Thou that flattereſt thy friend with league of lenitie, and with thy mates ſéekeſt his infamy; <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traytor was ſuch a deceiuer. And yée that are mercyleſſe to the aged, and to the poore in their ſickneſſe, the ſame qualitie hath the Diuell: if he haue thée in hell, he will fray thée, fry thée, and with brimſtome baſte thée, and in ſtead of coole li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, giue hot Lead: if thou wilt not come there, reſiſt all things that draw thée thither: <hi>Mat. 10.28. Feare him that can deſtroy both body and ſoule in hell.</hi> Good God, we pray thée, kéepe vs from <hi>Gehenna;</hi> it is thy mercy to ſpare vs, wée all deſerue thoſe torments. Bleſſed Trinitie, guide vs to felicitie: to thée be all honour and glory for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sit Deo laus in ſeculo. Sic fiat.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Comfort for the contrite.</head>
               <p>WE finde in ſacred Scriptures that few ſhall be ſaued in reſpect of the damned; and that the pangs are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable, infinite, and in explicable.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
                  <hi>He hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee, ô man, what is good; and what doeth the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of thee, but to doe iuſtly, and to loue mercy, and to walke humbly with thy God?</hi> We muſt turne from ſinne, and walke in newneſſe of life. To be a new creature is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: we ſinne oft, abhorre it, and preuent it. Repent with deteſtation, haue dayly renouation and amendment: haue Oyle with thy Lampe. Sauing grace and regeneration muſt be with a Chriſtian profeſſion. Bee faithfull, as <hi>Peter;</hi> well doing, as <hi>Dorcas:</hi> haue a good deſire, deſpayre not; no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, confidence; hate thy ſinne:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28</note> Chriſt calleth ſuch to giue them reſt: <hi>Mat. 12.20. A bruiſed reede ſhall he not breake,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19017:35"/> and ſmoking flaxe ſhall hee not quench.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.</note> Come to him with a ſparke of grace, hee will not deſpiſe thée. Repent truely, God will forgiue thée. Perſeuere in pietie to the end. Sorrow for ſinne, ioy in Chriſt, with two contrarieties at once in one ſubiect. Fight a good fight, finiſh thy courſe, kéepe the faith. Shrinke not like <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe vnder his burden. <hi>Pſa. 27.14. Waite on the Lord, be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen thine heart.</hi> Put on the whole Armour of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall weapons;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.12.</note> fight, and faint not. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation: for when he is tryed he ſhall receiue the Crowne of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that loue him.</hi> Reſiſt ſin ſtrongly, flye to Chriſt humbly, hée ſhed his teares and pretious bloud for thée. Wéepe thou with <hi>Peter,</hi> craue with blinde <hi>Bartemeus;</hi> ſée Chriſt by faith, and ſhew foorth fruits with <hi>Zacheus.</hi> Perſiſt with the woman of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</note> Imitate <hi>Dauid,</hi> voyd of <hi>puſillanimity,</hi> full of <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie,</hi> yet mourned; <hi>Pſa. 6.6. I am weary with my gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, all the night make I my bed to ſwimme; I water my couch with my teares. The ſacrifices of God are a broken Spirit:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.7. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 103.11.</note> 
                  <hi>a broken and contrite heart, ô God, thou wilt not deſpiſe. Ioy ſhall be in heauen ouer ſuch.</hi> Therefore with ſubmiſſion vſe contrition. <hi>For as the heauen is high aboue the earth: ſo great is his mercy toward them that feare him.</hi> God giue vs repentante, that we may be faithfull ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyers of Chriſts righteouſnes, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Dum spiro ſpero.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the ioyes of heauen prepared for Gods Children.</head>
               <p>FOr the faithfull penitent which warre againſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is prepared a place ſo ioyfull as is vnſpeakable: ſuch haue not onely <hi>immunitie,</hi> and freedome from bondage, but alſo intereſt to the priuiledges of Gods children, <hi>who are heyres with God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 7.14.</note> and coheyres with Chriſt in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: which is by the bloud of Ieſus, which waſheth vs white, without the which is no puritie. God impoſed the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19017:35"/> puniſhment for our ſinnes vpon him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> and he hath fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Iuſtice of his Father for them. The holy Spirit ſpeaketh to faithfull perſeuerers:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu.</hi> 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee thou faithfull vnto death, and I will giue thee the Crowne of life. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.21. To him that ouercometh will I graunt to ſit with me in my Throne, euen as I alſo ouercame, and am ſet downe with my Father in his Throne. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.4. And God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes: and there ſhall be no more death, neyther ſorrow, nor crying: neyther ſhall there be any more payne: for the former things are paſſed away. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 7. He that ouercommeth ſhall inherit all things, and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my ſonne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Eye hath not ſeene, nor care heard, neyther haue entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that loue him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Quéene of <hi>Sheba</hi> was come to <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſhee ſayd, <hi>1. King. 10.7. Behold, the halfe was not tolde mee.</hi> So Gods Saints ſhall then ſée that the thouſand part of thoſe ioyes were not tolde them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aug. <hi>O gaudium, ſuper gaudium, vincens omne gaudium, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra quod non est gaudium, quando intrabo inte, vt Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, qui habitat in te?</hi> O ioy aboue all ioyes, ſurpaſſing all ioyes, without which there is no ioy, when ſhall I enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that I may ſee my God that dwelleth in thee? <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectò in me totum non intrabit, ſed ego in illud totus intrabo.</hi> True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it will not enter wholly into me by my knowledge, that I may comprehend it, but I ſhall enter wholly into it by fruition that I may enioy it for euer.</hi> It is ſuch frée-hold, as is good for vs to build there; <hi>an inheritance incorruptible,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>and vndefiled, and that fadeth not away, reſerued in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for vs.</hi> There is beauty, brightneſſe, iubilation, exulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, mirth without mourning, heauenly harmony, delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, vnſpeakable. Saints ſhall ſing with Angels and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly habitants, <hi>All glory to the Trinitie.</hi> There is health, reſt, riches, abundance with continuance. A Paradiſe excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The Trinity in vnity ſhal ioy all hearts, his beauty is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19017:36"/> the longer viewed, the more deſired. O excellent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 34.29. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7.</note> brighter then the day Sunne: the ſkinne of <hi>Moſes</hi> face ſhone bright by being with God: gliſtering and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then ſhall men bee, being glorified and euer with God. Sinne ſhall no more diſquiet vs, the fleſh and the ſpirit ſhall then be at quiet; hauing perfect knowledge, perfect holineſſe. <hi>For now wee ſee through a Glaſſe, darkly: but then face to face:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Exo.</hi> 33.20. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>now I know in part; but then ſhall I know euen as alſo I am knowne.</hi> The Lord God ſaid; <hi>There ſhall no man ſee me and liue:</hi> but there we ſhall ſée him, and liue. All that reigne with Chriſt ſhall haue crownes of righteouſneſſe. <hi>2. Pet. 1.11.</hi> It is an euerlaſting Kingdome. <hi>Luke 14. Bleſſed is he that eateth bread in the kingdom of God.</hi> Ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the ſocietie of thoſe heauenly Citizens: the Region is Royall, and a Kingdome excéeding all kingdomes. <hi>Reu. 21.</hi> It is likned to a City of pure gold, <hi>which had no neede of the Sunne, neither of the Moone to ſhine in it: for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of GOD did lighten it, the Lambe is the light thereof: <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. And the gates of it ſhall not bee ſhut at all by day: for there ſhall be no night there.</hi> We heere are in danger of the Diuell and his darlings: but there ſhall be no enemie to hurt nor annoy. The glorious Heauen of heauens is not contaminate, but immaculate: there ſhal enter into it no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43. <hi>Eſay</hi> 25.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Then ſhall the righteous ſhine foorth as the Sunne in the kingdome of their Father.</hi> God will feaſt his faithfull: at his right hand is fulneſſe of ioy; euerlaſting ioy ſhall bee vpon them. <hi>Aug.</hi> There is myrth without mone, place without payne, life without labour, light without darknes: there youth alwaies flouriſheth and neuer decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; there is no torment felt, nor howling heard; no ſorrow ſéene, but poſſeſſion of ioyes euerlaſting. How glorious things are ſpoken of thée, thou Citie of God? true reioycing is in thy habitation. We ſhall bee rid from warfare, and bee in welfare, from ſinne, Satan and his adherents, from hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thirſt, heate, cold, wearineſſe, infirmities, dread, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, ſicknes, vexation, death &amp; damnation, &amp; be euer with God our preſeruer. Good children are glad to ſée their father
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19017:36"/> here; much more to behold our <hi>Heauenly Father,</hi> his ſonne our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> our <hi>Sanctifier</hi> there. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſprang in his Mothers wombe, at the tidings of our Sauiour.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk:</hi> 1.41.</note> Angells praiſed, and ſaid, <hi>Lu. <hi>2.24. Glory to God.</hi>
                  </hi> The ſhepheards went and ſaw him, publiſhed the newes, and gaue praiſe vnto God. Old <hi>Simeon</hi> took him in his arms, reioycing. Old <hi>Anna <hi>gaue thanks likewiſe vnto the Lord, and ſpake of him to all them that looked for redemption in</hi> Hieruſalem.</hi> Oh when men and all the hoaſts of Heauen ſing to his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> moſt glorious is that harmonie. Wée ſhall ſing in the preſence of God, <hi>Halleluiah, <hi>Saluation, glory, &amp; honour, &amp; power, be to the Lord our God.</hi>
                  </hi> Oh heauenly harmony, myrth, &amp; melody; Bleſſed are they that are called to the Lambs ſupper. <hi>M. Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Martyr belieued this beatitude, and thus did animate the young-man at the fire. Be of good comfort <hi>Brother,</hi> for we ſhall haue a merry ſupper with the Lorde this night. All faithful harts croſſed with calamity, and grieued for iniquity, be comforted, yée ſhall inherit a kingdom. We ſhal come to the mount <hi>Sion;</hi> not <hi>Sinay</hi> where the Law was giuen, but to the innumerable company of Angels. <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaide, for the ſight he ſaw on the mount. <hi>Lord, it is good for vs to be here.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 17.4</note> But then wee ſhalbe in light vnchangeable, and ſée Chriſt euer in felicity, whom his enemies had in obloquie. Thoſe Ioyes infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite paſſe all Ioyes finite. The voyce of Ioy and gladnes ſhal be euer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the righteous. Oh happy heires of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without our deſerts. <hi>Aug. Deus coronat dona ſua, non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita noſtra. <hi>God crowneth his owne gifts, not our merites. O bleſſe the Lord: who redeemeth thy life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſtruction:</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal:</hi> 103.4.</note> 
                  <hi>who crowneth thee with louing kindnes &amp; tender mercies. Feare not little flock,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lu:</hi> 12.32. <hi>Reu:</hi> 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>for it is your Fathers good pleaſure to giue you the kingdome. O let vs ſay, <hi>holy, holy, holy, Lord God Almightie, which was, &amp; is, &amp; is to come.</hi>
                  </hi> We ſhalbe Citizens with the ſaints, and of the houſhold of God, dignified and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified. In Ioy we ſhal reioyce that our names are written in heauen, francheſſed fréemen, irreuocably inrolled, as ſure, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſurer, then the eſtate of Angells. We ſhall haue the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Christs</hi> Reſurrection, and be <hi>manumiſſed</hi> from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19017:37"/> of death and deſtruction; Frée denizens, freed from miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and proude peoples malice. Thoſe Ioyes paſſe all <hi>Iubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lees.</hi> Good <hi>Ieſus</hi> bring vs to that bliſſe. As there is no equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie betwixt the Creator, and vs here ſinfull creatures: So is there none betwéene the ioyes of Heauen, and worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Theſe are ioyes tranſitory, the other Ioyes eternall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note>Wee ſhall be ioynt heires with Chriſt, and partakers of true happineſſe. There is no ſighing, ſinging. No heauineſſe, Ioyfulnes. No ignominie, glory. <hi>Holy, holy, holy,</hi> ſhall be euer aſcribed to <hi>Iehouah.</hi> The Virgins could learne the new ſong, which follow the Lambe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.</note> Oh the Ioyfull harmony that wee ſhall heare, and be glorified euer in glorie. Wee ſhall haue a palace vnſpeakable, being deliuered into the glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Children of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36</note> 
                  <hi>Neither can they doe any more, for they are equall to the Angels, and are the Children of GOD, being the children of the Reſurrection.</hi> If a man here ſicke heard thoſe ioyes, he would not féele his paine.</p>
               <p>Oh ioyfull ſhall we be when we be there, hearing, ſeeing and hauing vnſpeakable ioyes.<note place="margin">Aug:</note> 
                  <hi>Erit in Coelo domus tua aeterna, ſi modò bene in hoc tabernaculo vixeris: <hi>Thine houſe ſhall bee eternall in heauen, if now thou liueſt well in this tabernacle.</hi>
                  </hi> Loſe not that permanent Paradiſe for this pleaſure, which in reſpect thereof is paine: for the Barley corne, loſe not the pretious Pearle: for carnall copulation, eternall benediction: for a minute of ſelfe-will,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reu:</hi> 3.20.</note> millions of yéeres ioyfull. Ah, God forbid, he bids vs returne and reteyne him: <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the doore and knocke.</hi> Receiue him, and hee will receiue thée, to ſit in glory with his Maieſtie, which is a dignitie of all dignities.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.25.</note>This did mitigate <hi>Iobs</hi> miſery; <hi>For I know my Redeemer liueth, &amp; that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day vpon the earth: and though after my skin, wormes deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Phil. <hi>3. For our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation is in heauen, from whence alſo wee looke for the Sauiour, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who ſhall change our vile body, that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glorious body, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Comfort.</note> Our bodies ſhall be conformable to the body of Chriſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19017:37"/> our Head. <hi>We ſhall be like him:</hi> ill thoughts, bad motions, and perturbations ſhall be excluded. Wee heare this; but hée that beléeues it, and hopes to haue it, his affection is fixed in heauen. Therfore pray and repent, ſo ſhalt thou haue; what? A worldly commodity for which thou doſt venture ſoule and body? Ah, thou ſhalt haue a Throne of tryumph, excéeding all earthly treaſures, to reigne in ioyes for euer. If thou hadſt all earthly riches, plentiouſnes, pleaſures, and pleaſanteſt place on earth, with all elegant obiects, Princely proſpects, dainty delicates, muſicall Inſtruments, ſwéete ſingers, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, and fine ſauours, with all thy vnfained friends, and choyce of chiefe louers: yet all this were paine in reſpect of heauen, where we ſhall ouer be with our good God: to whom be all prayſe, honour, power, and glory now and euer, <hi>Amen:</hi> with heart and tongue, againe, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 66.18.</bibl> If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not heare me.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROV. 23.26.</bibl> My ſonne, giue me thine heart.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>¶ Pray heartily.</head>
            <p>OH heauenly Trinitie, one God in vnitie, to thee bee all honour. Glorious God, at thy brightnes, the Sunne, Moone and Starres are abaſhed and impure in thy ſight: much more I, a ſinfull creature, which by mine iniquities haue ſtained thoſe bright crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Omniſcient God, thou knowoſt my thoughts before I thinke them, and knoweſt me before I was. I was conceiued in ſin, borne in ſinne, in ſinne I liue. I am by nature the childe of wrath: O giue me grace to be borne from aboue, that I may enter into thy kingdome. I am not worthy to looke vp to thee, I deſerue to bee cast downe to hell; but I appeale to the Throne of thy mercy, in the Name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> my <hi>Sauiour,</hi> which calleth all penitent ſinners to him to giue them reſt.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19017:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> Oh <hi>Sauiour,</hi> refreſh my ſilly ſoule which cryes to thee out of my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full carkaſſe, that I may apply thy ſufferings, merits, and promiſes to my ſoule and conſcience, and be accepted through thy righteouſnes. My Lord and my God, out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſide iſſued the bloud of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and water of abſolution to purge me from pollution: thou ſtandeſt at the dore and knockeſt, giue me grace to open the dore of my heart; touch it with the finger of thy Spirit, that it maybe a fit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle to entertaine thee. Create in me a cleane heart, ô God; and renue a right ſpirit within me, that I may reſist all exill, and walke in righteouſnes and holineſſe all the dayes of my life. Let the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy loue wipe all teares from mine eyes: ſo come Lord Ieſus. Good God forgiue me all my ſinnes for Ieſus ſake, in whom thou art well pleaſed: cloath me with his righteouſnes, and behold me in him. I doe deſerue damnation, but hee hath payde my ranſome. Lord let me finde and feele thy mercy. Giue mee grace to redeeme the time, and ſpend it to thy prayſe. Bleſſe this Realme, our King, Queene, and Royall Progeny: bleſſe and comfort all thy children. Make vs loue thoſe things that thou doſt loue; and hate that thou hateſt, that we may keepe faith and a good conſcience. And if it be thy will, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue and conuert our enemies: Good God, prepare me and thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren fit for thy kingdome. O Chriſt giue vs grace to examine our ſelues whether thou be in vs, that we may expreſſe the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in our liues. Lord receiue our ſoules when we depart this life, that we may prayſe thee in heauen eternally. The which peace God bring vs, for Ieſus ſake that bought vs: to whome with thee, ô Father, and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one God, be all might, maieſtie, prayſe, honour, glory, power and dominion, now and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Watch and pray, prayſe God.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19017:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
